. GOOD AFTERNOON WELCOME TO THE
JULY 1ST 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND GUARDIAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR MENDELSON
PRESENT MENDELSON PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR AMILCAR MELGAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
PRESENT PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA SALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAMAKRISHNA LONI HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
RAMAKRISHNA LEARNING COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR RIGHTS
AS FIRST PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD,
INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY ESPECIALLY SUE INNES WHO
RECORDS WHO RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE
TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE.
MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
>> YES. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE HERE IN THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER WITHIN CITY HALL IN ROOM 250 ON THE SECOND
FLOOR IF YOU'D LIKE TO. IF YOU CAN'T BE PRESENT, YOU'D
LIKE TO WATCH THE BOARD'S PROCEEDINGS.
YOU CAN WATCH THEM ON AS IF GO VTV.ORG OR YOU CAN WATCH THE
LIVESTREAM AT W W W DOT S.F. GO VTV.ORG OR CHANNEL 26.
SUBMIT YOUR COMMENT IN WRITING SEND AN EMAIL TO BOSS AT S.F.
GOV TALK OR THROUGH THE POSTAL SERVICE ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON BE GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244
SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA 941082 IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A
REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES
ACT OR REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S
OFFICE TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS
ITEM NUMBER ONE ITEM ONE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE THE
SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY FOR THE MUNICIPAL
TRANSPORTATION AGENCY'S CONTINUED USE OF EXISTING
AUTOMATED RED LIGHT AND NO TURN ENFORCEMENT CAMERAS.
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM ONE?
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND GUARDIAN EYES SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD AI SUPERVISOR
MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR
SADR SADR I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EITHER ARE
WEAPONIZED WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER TWO ITEM TWO ORDINANCE
TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE TO EXTEND
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2026 THE WAIVER OF CERTAIN FIRST YEAR
PERMIT LICENSE AND BUSINESS REGISTRATION FEES FOR SPECIFIED
SMALL BUSINESSES THAT NEWLY FORM OR THAT OPEN A NEW
LOCATION. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO COMMITTEE
REPORTS. >> ITEM THREE WAS CONSIDERED BY
THE GOVERNMENT AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE AT A
SPECIAL MEETING ON FRIDAY, JUNE 27TH, 2025 AND WAS RECOMMENDED
AS A COMMITTEE REPORT. ITEM THREE IS A RESOLUTION THAT
APPROVES FOR PURPOSES OF THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODES OF 1986
AS AMENDED AUTHORIZING THE EXECUTION AND DELIVERY OF A
MULTIFAMILY HOUSING REVENUE NOTE IN ONE OR MORE SERIES
IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL NOT TO EXCEED 76 MILLION TO PROVIDE
FINANCING FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF AN 89 UNIT MULTIFAMILY
RENTAL HOUSING PROJECT LOCATED AT 65 SANTOS STREET KNOWN AS
THE SUNNYDALE HOPE S.F. BLOCK SEVEN.
THIS ITEM ALSO APPROVES THE FORM OF AN AUTHORIZING THE
EXECUTION OF MULTIPLE AGREEMENTS NOTES AND TERMS
AND CONDITIONS OF THE BACK TO BACK LOANS.
>> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM FOR ITEM FOUR WAS
CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT
A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY, JUNE 30TH AND WAS RECOMMENDED
AS A AS AMENDED WITH THE SAME TITLE AS A COMMITTEE REPORT.
ITEM FOUR IS AN ORDINANCE THAT AMENDS THE PLANNING
AND SUBDIVISION CODES TO ALLOW SEPARATE CONVEYANCE OF CERTAIN
ACCESSORY DWELLING UNITS AND ASSOCIATED PRIMARY
RESIDENCES AS CONDOMINIUMS AND AFFIRMS THE SECOND
DETERMINATION AND MAKES THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
>> FIRST MEMBER TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR
WALTON. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE A RESOLUTION AND IN MEMORIAM.
>> THE RESOLUTION IS URGING THE CITY TO ESTABLISH A SMALL
BUSINESS RELIEF FUND FOR MERCHANTS WHO WILL BE AFFECTED
BY THIS LATEST CREEK BRIDGE REPLACEMENT PROJECT ALONG THE
THIRD STREET BAYVIEW CORRIDOR. >> CONSTRUCTION WILL BEGIN AS
EARLY AS JANUARY 2027 AND WILL LAST FOR ABOUT THREE YEARS
AND WILL RESULT IN THE CLOSURE OF THIRD STREET BETWEEN MORAN
STREET AND CARGILL WAY. CUTTING OFF DIRECT ACCESS FOR
RESIDENTS, WORKERS AND CUSTOMERS.
THIS POSES A SERIOUS RISK TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD SMALL
BUSINESSES MANY OF WHICH ARE LEGACY IMMIGRANT OWNED
AND BLACK AND BROWN OWNED ESTABLISHMENTS THAT ARE ALREADY
FACED SYSTEMIC BARRIERS TO RECOVERY AND GROWTH.
THE BRIDGE PROJECT IS NECESSARY FOR PUBLIC SAFETY AND CLIMATE
RESILIENCE BUT THE CITY MUST NOT IGNORE THE ECONOMIC HARM
THAT COULD RESULT WITHOUT PROPER SAFEGUARDS IN PLACE.
SMALL BUSINESSES ALONG THEIR THIRD STREET CORRIDOR ARE
ALREADY SOUNDING THE ALARM THAT THIS PROJECT COULD DEVASTATE
THEIR CUSTOMER BASE AND MAKE IT IMPOSSIBLE TO STAY AFLOAT.
THE CITY HAS A RESPONSIBILITY TO PROTECT THESE MERCHANTS
AND ENSURE THEY ARE NOT LEFT BEHIND.
JUST LIKE HOW WE CREATED RELIEF FUNDS FOR MERCHANTS DOING OTHER
PROJECTS OR DURING THE PANDEMIC A CREATION OF A SMALL BUSINESS
RELIEF FUND DEDICATED TO THOSE IMPACTED BY THIS PROJECT SHOULD
INCLUDE GRANTS, RENT SUPPORT, MARKETING HELP AND TARGETED
OUTREACH. IF WE CAN FIND AND BUILD
CLIMATE RESILIENT INFRASTRUCTURE WE CAN ALSO FUND
RESILIENCE FOR OUR LOCAL ECONOMIES AND WORKING CLASS
NEIGHBORHOODS. I ALSO HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM.
IT IS WITH A HEAVY HEART THAT I JOIN THE POINT OF SERVING THE
PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO AND OUR ENTIRE CITY IN THE MORNING OF
THE SUDDEN DEATH OF BYRON RHETT .
BYRON WAS A DEDICATED PUBLIC SERVANT WHOSE DECADES OF
LEADERSHIP HELPED SHAPE THE SAN FRANCISCO WE KNOW TODAY.
>> FROM HIS EARLY YEARS AT THE SAN FRANCISCO REDEVELOPMENT
AGENCY WHERE HE LED CRITICAL REVITALIZATION EFFORTS AND BABY
HUNTERS POINT TO HIS TRANSFORMATIVE WORK AT THE PORT
OF SAN FRANCISCO. BYRON BROUGHT VISION COMPARE
VISION AND PURPOSE TO EVERYTHING HE TOUCHED.
AS PLANNING AND DEVELOPMENT DIRECTOR AND LATER AS CHIEF
OPERATING OFFICER, HE WAS THE QUIET FORCE BEHIND SOME OF THE
CITY'S MOST ICONIC PROJECTS. FROM THE REVITALIZATION OF PIER
ONE TO THE CREATION OF CRANE COVE PARK AND THE INNOVATION AT
MISSION ROCK AND PIER 70. >> BUT BYRON WAS MORE THAN A
LEADER. HE WAS A MENTOR, AN ADVOCATE
AND A BUILDER OF COMMUNITY. HE BELIEVED DEEPLY IN EQUITY,
PARTICULARLY IN UPLIFTING THE BAY VIEW.
AND HE LED WITH MORE THAN MOST INTEGRITY AND HEART.
HIS WORK LIVES ON NOT ONLY IN THE PLACES HE HELPED CREATE
BUT IN THE VALUES AND SPIRIT HE INSTILLED IN THOSE AROUND HIM.
SAN FRANCISCO IS BETTER BECAUSE OF BYRON.
I AM GRATEFUL FOR HIS LIFELONG COMMITMENT TO OUR CITY AND I
EXTEND MY DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO HIS WIFE ANDREA AND THEIR
SONS JUSTIN AND ZANE. MAY HIS MEMORY CONTINUE TO
GUIDE US AS WE BUILD A MORE INCLUSIVE AND CONNECTED SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES FIRST I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
IN SUPPORT OF THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF BROADCAST
EMPLOYEES AND TECHNICIAN LOCAL 51 WHO REPRESENTS KQED UNION
WORKERS AND THEIR EFFORTS TO DEMAND KQED LEADERSHIP TO
REINVEST IN LOCAL TELEVISION PROGRAMING.
STOP OUTSOURCING PRODUCTION WORK SUPPORT VALUABLE UNIONIZED
JOBS AND TO ENSURE THAT OUR PUBLIC MEDIA OUTLETS REFLECT
THE NEEDS OF OUR LOCAL COMMUNITIES IN THE BAY AREA.
KQED HAD ALREADY ELIMINATED ALL OF THEIR LOCAL NEWS PROGRAMING
IN 2023 AND HAS CONTINUED TO OUTSOURCE PRODUCTION WORK TO
NON-UNIONIZED FACILITIES. CONCLUDES RETREAT FROM LOCAL
TELEVISION PRODUCTION IS NOT ONLY A THREAT TO KQED EMPLOYEES
BUT ALSO SETS A DANGEROUS PRECEDENT FOR UNION LABORERS
AND THEIR SHARE VALUES WITH THE COMMUNITY THAT THEY SERVE.
ALSO COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
PUTTING SAN FRANCISCO ON THE RECORD TO OPPOSE STATE SENATE
BILL 70 NINE UNLESS AMENDED AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPERS
AND VARIOUS TENANTS GROUPS TO ATTEMPT TO SECURE AMENDMENTS
FROM THE BILL'S CHIEF SPONSOR SENATOR SCOTT WIENER.
AND YET THEY HAVE NOT BEEN SUCCESSFUL.
SO AS THEIR REPRESENTATIVE AND LOCALLY ELECTED POLICYMAKER
WE MUST STAND UP AND INTERVENE WHEN BAD STATE POLICY IS BEING
RUSHED THROUGH. WE MUST HAVE THIS DISCUSSION
IN PUBLIC NOT BEHIND CLOSED DOOR.
SB 79 WILL UNDO YEARS OF THOUGHTFUL COMMUNITY PLANNING
AND PUT SAN FRANCISCO'S TENANTS AND SMALL BUSINESSES AT RISK OF
DISPLACEMENT WITHOUT ANY PROTECTIONS PARTICULARLY AS WE
ANTICIPATE ADDITIONAL AMENDMENTS THAT WOULD ALSO
INCENTIVIZE THE DEMOLITION OF RENT CONTROL UNITS.
SB 79 PREDECESSOR TO SB 50 WAS REJECTED YEARS AGO FIVE YEARS
AGO BY THIS BOARD SUPERVISORS IN THIS CHAMBER BECAUSE OF ITS
OVERREACH AND ITS POTENTIAL THREATS TO LOW INCOME
AND COMMUNITIES OF COLOR IN VULNERABLE TRANSIT
ACCESSIBLE NEIGHBORHOODS ACROSS CITIES IN CALIFORNIA.
NOW I AM CONCERNED THAT SB 79 IS BEING FAST TRACKED WHILE SAN
FRANCISCO IS UNDERTAKING ITS OWN LOCAL CITYWIDE REZONING UP
ZONING THAT SEEKS TO BE COMPLIANCE WITH THE CALIFORNIA
DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT'S
APPROVED HOUSING ELEMENT THAT WE ALL ALREADY ADOPTED
UNANIMOUSLY. SB 79 WOULD COMPLETELY OVERRIDE
THE WORK OF THAT HOUSING ELEMENT TO CREATE PROTECTIONS
FOR PRIORITY EQUITY GEO GEOGRAPHIES PARTICULARLY IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS WHERE SMALL
BUSINESSES ARE ALREADY STRUGGLING WITH RENT AND COST
OF DOING BUSINESS. INCREASE WE CAN NOT BY BLINDLY
TRUST THAT TENANTS AND SMALL BUSINESS WILL SOMEHOW MAGICALLY
BE PROTECTED FROM DISPLACEMENT NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE THE RICHMOND
WILL BE MOST AT RISK OF BEING HOLLOWED OUT AS LOTS ARE MERGED
. >> RENTS ARE INCREASE
AND BUILDINGS ARE EMPTY OUT TO MAKE THEM MORE ATTRACTIVE TO
REAL ESTATE SPECULATOR ERS. >> THESE PLACES AND IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS HAVE NO PROTECTION FROM ANY OF THESE
SPECULATIVE BEHAVIORS. THERE ARE ALSO NO GUARANTEE
THAT ANY HOUSING ESPECIALLY AFFORDABLE HOUSING WILL EVEN BE
BUILT ANY TIME SOON. SOMEHOW OUR OWN LOCAL
ADMINISTRATION WILL REALLY HAVE TO RECOGNIZE THAT ULTIMATELY
THIS IS NOT A HOUSING BILL. IT IS A DEREGULATION
AND DEVELOPER GIVEAWAY BILL. IT IS NOT ABOUT ACTUALLY
BUILDING HOUSING. IT IS ABOUT MAKING THE LAND
ATTRACTIVE ENOUGH FOR SPECULATOR AND INVESTORS TO BUY
UP TO INCREASE THE PROFITS AT THE FRONT END.
AND LAND IS ALWAYS MORE ATTRACTIVE WITHOUT TENANTS.
AND IN THIS CASE FOR US THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
FINALLY THE BIGGEST PROBLEM WITH THIS BILL SB 79 IS THE
LACK OF FUNDING FOR AFFORDABILITY.
GOVERNOR GAVIN NEWSOM PUT OUT A BUDGET WITH NO FUNDING FOR
HOUSING AND HOMELESSNESS ONLY PUNITIVE MANDATES.
THIS IS MADNESS AND SAN FRANCISCO CANNOT CONTINUE TO
SHOULDER TOO ENTIRE RESPONSIBILITY FOR FUNDING
HOUSING INFRASTRUCTURE AND FREE MARKET.
>> AND WE CAN ALL KNOW HAVE LEARNED FROM YEARS OF HISTORY
IN SAN FRANCISCO WHEN WE TRIED TO BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THAT FREE MARKET HAS NEVER AND WILL NEVER BUILD US ENOUGH
AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR SAN FRANCISCANS AND THE REST I
SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN.
SUPERVISOR CHIN SUPERVISOR CHIN .
>> O SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES WITH APPRECIATION TO SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND HER STAFF
FOR THEIR WORK ON THIS PARTICULARLY MIKE FERA I AM
TODAY INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION THAT URGES BLUE SHIELD OF
CALIFORNIA AND THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA HEALTH SYSTEM TO
RESOLVE THEIR DISPUTE REGARDING REIMBURSEMENT FOR MEDICAL
SERVICES AND TREATMENT. THIS ONGOING CONTRACT DISPUTE
WAS POISED TO DISRUPT HEALTH CARE ACCESS FOR MANY THOUSANDS
OF SAN FRANCISCANS INCLUDING THOUSANDS OF OUR CITY WORKERS
AND RETIREES. IN A MATTER OF JUST A FEW DAYS.
THANKFULLY WE RECEIVED WORD YESTERDAY THAT THE PARTIES
EXTENDED THEIR NEGOTIATING DEADLINE FOR 30 DAYS TO AUGUST
9TH AND THAT THEY REMAIN IN NEGOTIATIONS.
>> STILL A LARGE SEGMENT OF OUR CITY'S WORKFORCE AND RETIREES
REMAIN UNCERTAIN ABOUT THE PROMISE OF ACCESS TO UCSF
HEALTH PHYSICIANS AND SERVICES THAT THEY RELIED UPON WHEN THEY
CHOSE BLUE SHIELD DURING OPEN ENROLLMENT FOR BLUE SHIELD TO
NOW POTENTIALLY ELIMINATE THESE HEALTH CARE OPTIONS.
IN MY IN THE MIDDLE OF A PLAN YEAR IS IN MY VIEW UNFAIR.
AND I WANT TO EXPRESS MY APPRECIATION TO CITY ATTORNEY
DAVID CHU AND HIS OFFICE FOR EXPLORING THE CITY'S LEGAL
OPTIONS IN THIS MATTER. I AGAIN WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR MELGAR WHO LIKE ME REPRESENTS MUCH OF UCSF
FOOTPRINT IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR COSPONSORING THIS RESOLUTION.
IT IS A RELATIVELY STRAIGHTFORWARD EXPRESSION OF
OUR COLLECTIVE HOPE AS A BOARD OF SUPERVISORS THAT WE URGE
UCSF HEALTH AND BLUE SHIELD TO RESOLVE THEIR DISPUTE BY
RENEWING THEIR CONTRACT AND THEREBY PRESERVING THEIR
MEMBERS ABILITY TO ACCESS THE CRUCIAL HEALTH CARE SERVICES
THEY SIGNED UP FOR OR IN THE EVENT THAT NO LONG TERM
SOLUTION BETWEEN BLUE SHIELD AND UCSF HEALTH IS POSSIBLE.
URGING THE PRIOR THE PARTIES TO AT LEAST COMMIT TO PRESERVE
EXISTING SERVICES FOR THE REMAINDER OF THE PLANNED YEAR
AND TO PROVIDE CERTAINTY FOR FUTURE BENEFITS FOR THE 2026
PLAN YEAR IN TIME FOR OPEN ENROLLMENT THIS FALL.
AS YOUR APPOINTEE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH SERVICES BOARD
I AM WORKING WITH HHS DIRECTOR RAY JIAN AND HIS TEAM AS WELL
AS CITY ATTORNEY CHU AND HIS TEAM TO MONITOR THIS SITUATION.
I KNOW ALL OF US HAVE BEEN HEARING FROM OUR CONSTITUENTS
AS WELL AS FROM OUR CITY WORKERS AND RETIREES ON THIS
MATTER. FOR THE CERTAINTY OF HEALTH
BENEFITS FOR ALL OF THEM AND THEIR FAMILIES, I HOPE I
CAN HAVE YOUR SUPPORT ON THIS RESOLUTION AS WELL AND THE REST
I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR HERR FIELDER.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TODAY TO DESIGNATE JULY 12TH AS CHU KANG DAY
IN HONOR OF THE FIFTH ANNIVERSARY OF THE DISTRICT
NINE BLOCK PARTY THAT CELEBRATES THE LIFE AND LEGACY
OF SEAN MONTERROSA. >> AS IT HAS EVERY YEAR SINCE
20 20, SEAN MONTERROSA HAD A BRIGHT, BEAUTIFUL AND LIMITLESS
LIFE AHEAD OF HIM. HE WAS AMBITIOUS, LOVED BY HIS
COMMUNITY, WAS CONSTANTLY LOOKING FOR WAYS TO UPLIFT
YOUTH AND THOSE AROUND HIM AND WAS DEEPLY PROUD OF HIS
ROOTS. >> AS YOU KNOW, HIS LIFE WAS
TAKEN FROM HIM FAR TOO SOON BY A VALLEJO POLICE OFFICER
IN 2020. BUT HIS MEMORY AND LEGACY LIVE
ON IN THE COMMUNITY THAT CONTINUES TO ORGANIZE AGAINST
POLICE BRUTALITY AND HIS POWERFUL SISTERS WHO CONTINUE
TO FIGHT FOR JUSTICE NOT ONLY FOR THEIR FAMILY BUT OTHERS
IMPACTED BY POLICE BRUTALITY AND IN THE STRUCTURES, ART
AND PROGRAMS THAT HAVE BEEN CREATED IN HIS MEMORY INCLUDING
THE SHAWN MONTERROSA. >> KNOWLEDGE A COMMUNITY
LIBRARY THAT PROVIDES BILINGUAL BOOKS ABOUT SOCIAL JUSTICE.
A MURAL IN HIS HONOR AT 24TH AND SOUTH VENICE.
AND THE STREET NAMES ON MONTROSE BOULEVARD NEXT TO
HAILEY PARK WHERE HE GREW UP. >> CAN DAY IS NAMED AFTER
SHAWN'S CHILDHOOD NICKNAME. >> IT IS A BLOCK PARTY FULL OF
ART, MUSIC ACTIVITIES AND CONVERSATION ABOUT THE
ISSUES SHAWN CARED ABOUT AND ABOVE ALL ELSE.
IT IS A DAY FOR COMMUNITY HEALING.
SHAWN WAS A YOUNG LEADER WHO WORKED ON SO MANY ISSUES TO
MAKE THIS A BETTER WORLD FOR YOUNG PEOPLE.
IT IS WITH THAT SPIRIT THAT THIS RESOLUTION HONORS HIM
AND HIS FAMILY BY DESIGNATING THIS SPECIAL DAY ON ITS FIFTH
ANNIVERSARY AS TWO CAN DAY AND SAN FRANCISCO.
I WANT TO THANK EARLY CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISORS CHEN
MELGAR AND WALTON. AND I ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK
MICHELLE AND ASHLEY MONTERROSA FOR THEIR TIRELESS WORK TO
HONOR THEIR BROTHER AND BUILD COMMUNITY AROUND HIS BRIGHT
LIGHT. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING THIS SHARED HOUSING REFORM ACT AN ORDINANCE THAT IS
MEANT TO MODERNIZE THE CITY'S OUTDATED DEFINITION OF FAMILY
IN THE PLANNING CODE TO EXPAND ACCESS TO SHARED HOUSING
AND BRING SAN FRANCISCO INTO COMPLIANCE WITH STATE HOUSING
REGULATIONS. >> SAN FRANCISCO IS A CITY OF
RENTERS AND IN OUR CITY'S PRESENT HOUSING AFFORDABILITY
CRISIS WE MUST DO ALL THAT WE CAN TO SUPPORT HOUSEHOLDS
SHARED BETWEEN UNRELATED ROOMMATES.
THESE HOMES ARE A FIRST STEP TO INDEPENDENCE AND A FIRST STEP
TO A LIFE IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR SO MANY.
BUT UNDER CURRENT LAW MANY OF THESE HOUSEHOLDS MAY BE AT RISK
OF ENFORCEMENT ACTION FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR NOT
FITTING UNDER AN OUTDATED DEFINITION OF FAMILY.
SAN FRANCISCO'S ZONING LAWS TRY TO TELL PEOPLE WHO COUNTS AS A
FAMILY. IF WE WANT TO BE A MORE
AFFORDABLE CITY WE HAVE TO START BY LEGALIZING THE WAY
REAL SAN FRANCISCANS LIVE. >> UNDER CURRENT LAW,
HOUSEHOLDS OF MORE THAN FIVE UNRELATED TO INDIVIDUALS WHO DO
NOT COOK MEALS TOGETHER MUST MEET GROUP HOUSING STANDARDS
OFTEN MAKING OLDER HOMES WITH HOUSEMATES TECHNICALLY
NON-COMPLIANT. SO TODAY I'M INTRODUCING THE
SHARED HOUSING REFORM ACT WHICH REMEDIES THIS IN SEVERAL WAYS.
ONE IT REPLACES THE TERM FAMILY WITH HOUSEHOLD THROUGHOUT THE
PLANNING CODE. TWO IT REMOVES NUMERIC LIMITS
ON UNRELATED RESIDENTS LIVING TOGETHER.
>> THREE IT ESTABLISHES A NINE LEASE THRESHOLD TO DISTINGUISH
SHARED HOUSEHOLDS FROM INSTITUTIONAL GROUP HOUSING.
>> FOUR IT RECOGNIZES SHARED FINANCIAL RESPONSIBLE BILITY
LIKE RENT AND UTILITIES AS THE DEFINING FEATURE OF A HOUSEHOLD
. AND LASTLY IT ALIGNS LOCAL LAW
WITH STATE MANDATES TO TREAT COMMUNITY CARE AND RECOVERY
FACILITIES SERVING SIX OR FEWER INDIVIDUALS AS DWELLING UNITS.
THE PLANNING CODE WAS AMENDED TO LIMIT THE NUMBER OF
UNRELATED ROOMMATES THAT COULD LIVE TOGETHER AROUND THE TIME
OF THE 1978 CITY WIDE DOWN ZONING PROCESS OFTEN PREVENTING
BUILDERS AND DEVELOPERS FROM BUILDING SHARED HOUSING
AND CO-OP HOUSING OPTIONS TO AVOID ENFORCEMENT BY THE CITY.
THE CITY'S PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS TAKEN 14 ENFORCEMENT
ACTIONS SINCE 2020 REVIEWING THE DEFINITION OF FAMILY
AND ITS INCLUSION OF NON-RELATED HOUSEHOLDS WAS AN
EXPLICIT IMPLEMENTATION RECOMMENDATION OF THE HOUSING
ELEMENT TO ENSURE FAIR, INCLUSIVE AND EQUITABLE HOUSING
STANDARDS. >> THIS IS ABOUT FAIRNESS
AND THIS LEGISLATION RECOGNIZING THAT TODAY'S
FAMILIES AND CHOSEN FAMILIES COME IN MANY FORMS.
IF IT'S GOOD ENOUGH FOR OUR INCLUSIVE VALUES SHOULD BE GOOD
ENOUGH FOR OUR ZONING CODE AS WELL.
>> THANKS TO JOSH MASSAD MORE MARK HOGAN AND LISA ZAUNER FOR
BRINGING THIS ISSUE TO MY ATTENTION FROM THE COMMUNITY.
>> THANKS TO HEATHER GOODMAN AND JULIA GORKA NELSON FROM THE
CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE RENO COOPER AND JESSICA GUTIERREZ.
GARCIA FROM MY OFFICE AND LIZ WATTIE, ERIN STARR, DAN SNYDER
AND AUDREY MALONEY FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR THEIR
HELP ON THIS LEGISLATION. LASTLY, THANK YOU TO MY
COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR SAUDER, CHERYL AND MELGAR FOR THEIR
EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MARKMAN SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN THANK YOU
MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO UPDATE THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
SECTIONS GOVERNING THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SHELTER BASED PROGRAM
FUNDS TO ENSURE THAT OUR LAWS REFLECT THE REALITY OF HOW
GENDER BASED VIOLENCE PREVENTION WORK IS BEING
DELIVERED IN SAN FRANCISCO. AS PART OF LAST YEAR'S BUDGET
PROCESS IT WAS CONTEMPLATED THAT THE GENDER BASED VIOLENCE
GRANT PORTFOLIO WOULD MOVE FROM THE DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT. THAT TRANSITION IS NOW WELL
UNDERWAY, MOSTLY CONDUCTING A FULL PROCUREMENT PROCESS
IN LATE 2000 IN LATE 2024 AND EARLY 2025.
THE NEW GRANT AGREEMENTS WITH COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS
ARE SET TO BEGIN TODAY, JULY 1ST.
NOTWITHSTANDING THAT TRANSITION ,OUR ADMINISTRATIVE CODE STILL
ASSIGNS OVERSIGHT OF THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SHELTER BASED
PROGRAM FUND TO THE DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN.
THIS ORDINANCE CORRECTS THAT OUTDATED PROVISION AND FORMALLY
MOVES ADMINISTRATION TO FUND THE MOST.
THE DEPARTMENT NOW CHARGED WITH OVERSEEING THIS WORK.
THE LEGISLATION ALSO ADDRESSES A NUMBER OF OTHER
INCONSISTENCIES AND OUTDATED REFERENCES IN THE CODE.
I WANT TO THANK THE DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN THE
COUNTY CLERK'S OFFICE, JESSIE MINORITY IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE AND MELANIE MATHESON AND MY OFFICE FOR THEIR WORK ON
THE LEGISLATION. I VERY MUCH WANT TO THANK
BEVERLY UPTON AND AMBERLY CROSS FOR IDENTIFYING SOME OF THE
ISSUES THAT NEEDED TO GET ADDRESSED IN THE LEGISLATION
AND FOR REVIEWING AND PROVIDING FEEDBACK AS IT EVOLVED.
AND OF COURSE FOR THEIR ADVOCACY IN SUPPORTING VICTIMS
OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE. AND I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
CHERYL FOR HIS CO-SPONSORSHIP AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SADR.
SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER. THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION
OF NEW BUSINESS. >> ALL RIGHT, WE HAVE THREE
MINUTES UNTIL 230 AND SO WE COULD CONCEIVABLY HEAR FROM ONE
OR PERHAPS TWO MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC.
IF ANYBODY WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE THEIR PUBLIC COMMENT
NOW AND GET THEMSELVES OUT OF HERE.
ALL RIGHT. WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO
MINUTES. PLEASE STEP UP.
OKAY. >> STARTING TODAY ONE.
>> DO YOU LIKE MY NEW. >> THEY LEAVE GLASSES.
YOU KNOW THESE ONES? YEAH.
>> I SHOULD PUT THEM LIKE THIS BUT IT WOULD BE A BIT STUPID,
RIGHT? OKAY.
ANYWAY. YEAH.
CARPENTER I LIKE JESUS. OKAY, SO WHAT'S COMING HERE?
I SAID YOU DON'T REMEMBER? THERE'S SOMETHING WRONG.
A FIFTH AROUND THE FOURTH 5TH OF JULY.
I SAID LATE JANUARY THEY'RE GOING TO BE AN ATTACK ON US,
EVERYONE. >> WE DON'T KNOW YET.
THEY CALL THIS A FALSE FLAG. I THINK IT'S JUST WE KNOW IT'S
COMING. SO WHAT'S YOUR EXCUSE ME FOR
THE. >> MAKE SURE YOU ARE PROTECTED
ENOUGH BECAUSE THERE ARE GOING TO BE SOME REPERCUSSIONS AFTER
COMING UP. >> SO MARK MY WORD IF IF IT
DOESN'T HAPPEN, IT'S BECAUSE I MANAGED TO.
>> WHAT IT'S YOU UNDERSTAND THE PREDICTION IS PRECISE OTHERWISE
NOT ASK ME HOW I KNOW THAT'S. >> CONGRATULATIONS TO THE
MAYOR TO HAVE ACCEPTED FINALLY TO STOP TAKING DOWN THE 5G
TOWERS EVEN THOUGH HE DOESN'T WANT TO CONFESS ABOUT IT YET
BECAUSE HIS HANDLER MAY BE A BIT PROBLEMATIC FOR THAT.
>> OKAY SO YOU TWO HERE YOU GET TO DO THE JOB.
START DOING WHAT I SAID DON'T BOAST ABOUT IT TOO MUCH.
>> WHAT HAPPENED TO THE WHY NO REFUGEE ON A TREASURE ISLAND
WOULD HAVE BEEN BACK. WHAT ARE YOU DOING THE ONLY
OTHER WAY LIFE REFUGEE FOR MAMMALS NOT CEMETERY ON
TREASURE ISLAND. >> CAN CREATE SOME JOBS AS
WELL. AND HE'S GOING TO BE BEAUTIFUL.
SO ACTUALLY CONGRATULATIONS FOR THINKING ABOUT IT ALREADY.
>> I KNOW YOU DO. SO GOOD NOW PROCEED BECAUSE
HE'S GOING TO HAPPEN ANYWAY. EXAMPLE TECHNOLOGY HERE IN THE
FUTURE WE'RE GOING TO CREATE NO MORE STREETLIGHTS, NO MORE
TRAFFIC LIGHTS BASED ON EVERYTHING WITH TECHNOLOGY
TELLING YOU IN ADVANCE IT'S COMING TO SEE THAT'S HOW YOU
USE TECHNOLOGY IN A PROLIFIC AND BENEFICIAL WAY FOR EVERYONE
. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENT.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER PETER ALEXANDER THANK YOU.
THIS 4TH OF JULY WE WILL NOW TRULY BE CELEBRATING FREEDOM
AND LIBERTY AND JUSTICE. WELL EXCEPT FOR GREEN BERET
SURGEON DR. JEFFREY MACDONALD WHO'S STILL IN PRISON 54 YEARS
LATER FOR BLOWING THE WHISTLE ON BUSH'S HEROIN FOR WHICH THEY
TERMINATED THE LIFE OF HIS PREGNANT WIFE AND TWO
DAUGHTERS. >> AND EXCEPT FOR THE TENS OF
THOUSANDS OF VETS THAT ARE SITTING IN PRISON BECAUSE THEY
WERE SELF-MEDICATING WITH THE CIA'S HEROIN OR PERHAPS THE 229
AMERICAN ANCHOR OUTS IN SAUSALITO THAT HAD THEIR
VESSELS SEIZED AND CRUSHED. AND ONE OF THE TREATIES THERE'S
STILL SO MANY TREATIES OR SO MY SOLDIERS ARE ETERNAL.
>> YEAH. TUPAC SHAKUR SAID THAT THIS
JULY 4TH 2025 BEAUTIFUL AND ALIVE I AM PETER I AM ONE
WITH THE GREAT SPIRIT BOTH SEEN AND UNSEEN THE POWER OF LOVE.
I'M CALLING UPON ALL WARRIORS TO PLAY SANTANA'S TURN YOUR
LIGHTS ON AND BOB DYLAN'S YOU GOT TO SERVE SOMEBODY FOR
CALIFORNIA IS THE MOST POWERFUL STATE WITH THE MOST POWERFUL
WARRIORS NOW UNDER MY COMMAND ROSEBUD.
>> ROSEBUD NO FLOWER WITH THE CHRISTO'S LIGHTS OVERCOMING
POWER TRUMP COMMANDED POWER WITH A MILITARY PARADE THE
ILLUSORY OPPOSITION WITH ITS 5 MILLION PROTESTERS AND PAID
AGITATORS. SO THEM SHOWED US THEIR POWER
AND THE NEW POPE WITH UTTERANCES AND PAGEANTRY SHOWED
US HIS POWER. I SUGGEST REGARDING THEM ALL BY
PLAYING SMILING FACES BY THE UNDISPUTED TRUTH.
I AM PETER. I AM COMMANDING ALL HORN
BLOWERS, SEA CAPTAINS, CAPTAINS OF TRUCKING OF ALL CAR
AND BIKER CLUBS AND ALL DOG SOLDIERS AND WARRIORS OF THE
HOLY SPIRIT BE RELEASING WITHOUT CEASING THE POWER ALL
MIGHTY OVERCOMING ALL THIS WORLDLY CORRUPTIONS FOR ALL
TIME IS NOW AND NOW IS THE TIME I SAY YOU HEAR IT IS SO IT IS
DONE THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT. WE WILL NOW TAKE A BREAK FROM
PUBLIC COMMENT AND GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER.
>> MADAM CLERK, IT'S NOW TIME FOR THE RECOGNITION OF
COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> WE WERE GOING TO START WITH
SIX BUT WE'RE NOT STARTING WE ARE GOING TO NOT OKAY.
WE'RE COME BACK TO SIX. ALL RIGHT.
>> IS D-10 READY? >> SURPRISED?
WELL, ARE YOU READY OR COME BACK?
YOU'RE READY. ALL RIGHT, LET'S DO DISTRICT
TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
PRESIDENT MADAM AND COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY DISTINCT HONOR
TO PRESENT THE SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO MISS DIANE GRAY
IN CELEBRATION OF HER EXTRAORDINARY CAREER IN HER
WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT. MISS GREAT, COULD YOU COME UP
AND DIANE GRAY IS THE EMBODIMENT OF WHAT IT MEANS TO
SERVE COMMUNITY WITH PURPOSE PRIDE EMPOWER A PROUD SAN
FRANCISCO NATIVE AND 48 YEAR RESIDENT OF BAYVIEW HUNTERS
POINT, DIANE HAS DEDICATED HER LIFE TO UPLIFTING OUR YOUTH,
EMPOWERING FAMILIES AND STRENGTHENING THE FUTURE OF
OUR CITY THROUGH DECADES OF TIRELESS WORK IN EDUCATION,
GOVERNMENT AND COMMUNITY ORGANIZING, DIANE HAS REMAINED
ROOTED IN THE BELIEF THAT WHEN ONE OF US SUCCEEDS WE ALL
SUCCEED. A PRINCIPLE SHE HAS INSTILLED
IN GENERATIONS THROUGH HER SIGNATURE MANTRA MY SUCCESS IS
YOUR SUCCESS AS CO-FOUNDER OF 100% COLLEGE PREP DIANE
TRANSFORMED THE EDUCATIONAL LANDSCAPE FOR HUNDREDS OF
STUDENTS FROM BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT AND ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO
. HER VISION AND LEADERSHIP HAVE
NOT ONLY PAVED THE WAY FOR COUNTLESS FIRST GENERATION
COLLEGE STUDENTS BUT HAS ALSO HELPED ENSURE THAT OUR YOUNG
PEOPLE ARE SUPPORTED FROM HIGH SCHOOL AND THROUGH COLLEGE
COMPLETION THROUGH INITIATIVES LIKE JUMPSTART TO COLLEGE
AND GET THROUGH COLLEGE. DIANE CREATED A MODEL FOR LONG
TERM SUCCESS ESPECIALLY FOR STUDENTS TOO OFTEN OVERLOOKED.
>> DIANE HAS ALSO MADE AN INDELIBLE IMPACT AS EDUCATION
DIRECTOR AT YOUNG COMMUNITY DEVELOPERS AND IN HER ROLES
ACROSS MULTIPLE CITY DEPARTMENTS INCLUDING THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE COMMISSION. >> I MEAN I'M SORRY THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION, SAN FRANCISCO
TREASURER'S OFFICE AND SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL
DISTRICT. >> SHE HAS SERVED OVER 20 YEARS
AS A CITY AND COUNTY EMPLOYEE ALWAYS BRINGING INTEGRITY,
COMPASSION AND EXCELLENCE TO HER WORK.
>> HER LEGACY IS NOT ONLY IN HER PROFESSIONAL
ACCOMPLISHMENTS BUT IN HER CIVIC LEADERSHIP.
DIANE HAS BEEN A VITAL FORCE IN EFFORTS LIKE THE BLACK TO
THE FUTURE INITIATIVE. MY BROTHER AND SISTERS KEEPER
MEGA BLACK SAN FRANCISCO AND NUMEROUS ADVISORY BODIES
AND COMMISSIONS ARE DEDICATED TO ENSURING THAT EQUITY
AND JUSTICE ARE MORE THAN JUST IDEALS BUT LIVED REALITIES
IN SAN FRANCISCO. FOR HER DECADES OF SERVICE,
DIANE HAS RIGHTFULLY EARNED COUNTLESS ACCOLADES INCLUDING
THE SAN FRANCISCO'S WARRIORS IMPACT AWARD, JEFFERSON SILVER
AWARD AND HONORS FROM NATIONAL AND LOCAL BLACK ORGANIZATION.
BUT NO AWARD CAN FULLY CAPTURE THE PROFOUND IMPACT DIANE HAS
HAD ON THE CITY AND THE PEOPLE IN IT.
DIANE YOUR RETIREMENT MARKS THE CLOSE OF A POWERFUL CHAPTER BUT
YOUR LEGACY WILL CONTINUE TO SHAPE THE FUTURE OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR GENERATIONS TO COME.
ON BEHALF OF THE RESIDENTS OF DISTRICT TEN AND A GRATEFUL
CITY, I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR UNWAVERING SERVICE, YOUR
LOVE FOR COMMUNITY AND YOUR BELIEF IN OUR YOUTH.
WITH DEEPEST RESPECT AND ADMIRATION.
WE THANK YOU AND CONGRATULATE YOU ON YOUR RETIREMENT.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
HONORABLE SUPERVISOR OF THE ILLUSTRIOUS DISTRICT TEN.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR HONORING ME TODAY AND AND TO THE REST OF
THE BOARD COMMISSIONERS AND LAW PRESIDENT.
IT HAS BEEN TRULY A BLESSING TO SUPPORT AND HELP OUR YOUNG
PEOPLE FLY WHEN THEY DIDN'T KNOW THEY HAD WINGS.
AND IN 1999 MY COUSIN AND I WERE JUST VOLUNTEERING IN OUR
COMMUNITY AND HAD A CONVERSATION WITH A GROUP OF
YOUNG TEENS, YOUNG WOMEN THAT WE WERE HELPING
AND VOLUNTEERING WITH AND HAD A CONVERSATION ABOUT COLLEGE
AND CAREER AND DIDN'T LIKE WHAT WE HEARD.
>> AND SO WE JUST GOT TOGETHER AND A ONE DAY A WEEK GIRLS
GROUP TURNED INTO A SECOND DAY OF A COLLEGE CLUB AND WE HAD NO
INTENTIONS OF THIS. 25 YEARS LATER IN NONPROFIT
WORLD WE WERE JUST SUPPORTING YOUNG PEOPLE IN OUR COMMUNITY
AND MAKING SURE THAT THEY HAD WHAT THEY NEED TO COME BACK
AND BE GREAT CITIZENS IN OUR IN OUR CITY.
>> AND SO TODAY AFTER 25 YEARS IT'S TIME TO PASS THE TORCH.
>> WE HAVE GOTTEN HUNDREDS OF YOUNG PEOPLE IN COLLEGE
AND THROUGH COLLEGE TO PERSIST THROUGH COLLEGE.
TODAY WE HAVE HUNDREDS OF STUDENTS WHO HAVE COLLEGE
DEGREES. >> THEY HAVE MASTER'S DEGREES
AND WE HAVE TWO THAT HAVE THEIR THEIR PH.D. OR IDS AND A GRAD
AND A GRAND NUMBER OF THOSE STUDENTS COME FROM THE BAYVIEW
HUNTERS POINT COMMUNITY. BUT WE ALSO SERVE YOUNG PEOPLE
ALL OVER OUR CITY AND WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO PARTNER WITH MANY
OF THE ORGANIZERS ASIANS HERE IN THIS CITY AND BEYOND.
>> I HAVE MY MY TEAM HERE OF COACHES COULD NOT DO THIS
ALONE. I WOULD LOVE FOR THEM TO STAND
UP AND JUST BE SEEN. >> THE WORK THAT WE'VE DONE HAS
BEEN IN COMMUNITY AND REALLY QUICKLY THE WORK THAT WE HAVE
DONE. AS SUPERVISOR WALTON JUST
MENTIONED HAS BEEN IN COMMUNITY AND IT'S ALSO BEEN IN OUR
SCHOOLS. AND WHEN I LEFT CITY HALL AS A
SPECIAL ASSISTANT TO THE TREASURER I WENT OVER TO THE
SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT BECAUSE OF THE WORK
THAT I WAS DOING AND THE COMMUNITY TOOK A PRETTY GOOD
PAY CUT. BUT I HAD PRAYED ABOUT IT AND I
KNEW WHAT MY MISSION WAS AND GOD HAD GIVEN ME THAT
MISSION AND THAT PURPOSE. AND THEN I LEFT THE UNIFIED
SCHOOL DISTRICT TO FOCUS ON THE WORK THAT WE WERE DOING IN THE
COMMUNITY. SO AGAIN, IT'S BEEN A BLESSING
TO WORK WITH OUR YOUNG PEOPLE TO SEE THEM COME BACK AND MAKE
A DIFFERENCE IN OUR CITY. A NUMBER OF THEM HAVE WORKED
RIGHT HERE WITH OUR CITY AND CITY HALL AND CITY
AGENCIES. >> AND SO THAT IS THE WORK OF
100% AND THAT'S THE WORK THAT WILL CONTINUE ON IN THE THE
NEXT CHAPTER AND THE NEXT JOURNEY.
THE NEXT PHASE OF 100% WILL BE IN THAT LEADERSHIP.
SO I FOCUS ON CULTIVATING THE NEXT GROUP OF LEADERS SO THAT
THEY WILL CONTINUE THIS WORK THAT WE NEED SO DESPERATELY TO
DO AND THAT WE NEED AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO WORK WITH OUR
SCHOOL DISTRICT AS WELL. >> SIDE BY SIDE WITH THEM TO
MAKE SURE THAT OUR YOUNG PEOPLE HAVE WHAT THEY NEED.
SO AGAIN, THANK YOU SO MUCH. AGAIN, IT'S BEEN A TRUE
BLESSING TODAY IS MY FIRST DAY AS A RE AS BILLY WANG SAID.
REQUIREMENT WE WHY YOU'RE MEANT BECAUSE I WILL STAY YOU KNOW I
WILL STAY IN THE COMMUNITY AND I WILL CONTINUE TO DO THIS
WORK AS A FOREVER FOUNDER SO THANK YOU AGAIN SO MUCH.
>> APPRECIATE YOUR TIME AND YOUR RECOGNITION TODAY.
THANK YOU IS AND WE'RE STILL WAITING SUPERVISOR DORSEY RIGHT
OKAY LET'S GO TO DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SLAUGHTER RIGHT
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MAN I MEAN YOU KNOW THE CALENDAR MAY SAY
THAT PRIDE IS OVER BUT SINCE WE'RE SAN FRANCISCO WE'RE GOING
TO KEEP THINGS GOING A LITTLE LONGER AND TODAY RECOGNIZE
SCOTT TAYLOR, THE OWNER OF THE CINCH SALOON.
SCOTT, WOULD YOU COME JOIN US AT THE PODIUM?
THE CINCH OPENED IN 1974 ON POLK STREET MEANING IT IS ONE
OF THE CITY'S OLDEST GAY BARS AND THAT IS EXACTLY WHY IN THE
PAST FEW YEARS THERE'S BEEN SO MUCH CONCERN AND ANXIETY AS
RUMORS SWIRLED ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THE CENTURY.
BUT TO OUR GREAT RELIEF, SCOTT STEPPED IN LAST MONTH AS THE
NEW OWNER AND FROM TALKING TO HIM AND HEARING FROM HIS
PATRONS I KNOW HE'S DOING THIS BECAUSE HE FEELS A
RESPONSIBILITY AND A CALLING TO CARRY THIS INCH FORWARD.
SCOTT BRINGS MORE THAN TWO DECADES OF HOSPITALITY
EXPERIENCE AND HE'S A LONGTIME LOVE IN HISTORY AT THE BENCH HE
FIRST VISITED MORE THAN 20 YEARS AGO AND HE EVEN HAD HIS
FIRST DATE WITH HIS PARTNER AT THE CENTURY TODAY THE SYNCH
MIGHT BE AMONG THE LAST GAY BARS ON POLK STREET, BUT IT
REMINDS US OF THE ROLE THAT POLK STREET HAS PLAYED IN OUR
LGBT Q PLUS HISTORY. SOME OF THE MOST PROMINENT GAY
BARS OF THE 1950S AND 60S WERE ON POLK STREET CORNER POCKET
JUMPING FROG AND BUSBY'S THE FIRST GAY BUSINESSES
ASSOCIATION IN THE ENTIRE COUNTRY TAVERN GUILD OF SAN
FRANCISCO WAS COMPRISED MOSTLY OF POLK STREET MERCHANTS
AND THE FIRST SAN FRANCISCO PRIDE PARADE HAPPENED NOT ON
MARKET STREET OR IN THE CASTRO BUT ALONG POLK STREET IN 1972.
I THINK SCOTT SAID IT BEST WHEN HE SAID IN A CITY WHERE SO MANY
LGBTQ PLUS LANDMARKS HAVE DISAPPEARED, PROTECTING THESE
SPACES IS MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVER.
THIS ISN'T JUST A BAR IT'S A LIVING PIECE OF HISTORY.
AND NOW IT IS SECURED FOR THE NEXT GENERATION TO CELEBRATE,
GATHER AND THRIVE. SCOTT I WANT TO APPRECIATE ALL
THE WORK THAT YOU'RE DOING THAT YOU HAVE DONE AND THAT YOU WILL
DO GOING FORWARD. IT IS NOT EASY TO TAKE A LEAP
INTO INTO WHAT YOU'RE DOING INTO OWNING A SMALL BUSINESS
IN SAN FRANCISCO INTO OWNING A BAR AND ESPECIALLY ONE WITH
SUCH HIGH EXPECTATIONS SUCH A TREASURED PLACE IN SO MANY
PEOPLE'S HEARTS. SO THANK YOU FOR DOING THAT.
THANK YOU FOR MAKING SURE THAT THE CENTRAL LIVE ON FOR ANOTHER
GENERATION. AND WITH THAT WOULD LOVE TO
HEAR IF YOU WANT TO SHARE ANY WORDS WELL THANK YOU VERY MUCH
FOR THE RECOGNITION I VERY MUCH APPRECIATE THIS COMING OUT
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND ESPECIALLY SUPERVISOR
SADR'S OFFICE WE DO WHAT WE CAN TO PRESERVE THESE SPACES FOR
THE COMMUNITY BECAUSE THEY ARE SHRINKING AND IT'S OUR
RESPONSIBLE BILITY AS A COMMUNITY TO KIND OF UPLIFT
THESE POSITIONS AND TO BE ABLE TO KIND OF KEEP THESE SAFE
SPACES OPEN FOR PEOPLE MOVING FORWARD.
SO THANK YOU AGAIN. I APPRECIATE THE RECOGNITION
AND LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING TOGETHER, MOVING FORWARD
I WOULD NOTE THAT WE HAVE BEEN JOINED BY FORMER CONGRESSMAN
PRESIDENT OF THE CALIFORNIA STATE SENATE AND DEMOCRATIC
PARTY CHAIR OF THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA JOHN BURTON AS WELL
AS AS WELL AS OUR FORMER COLLEAGUE AND FORMER PRESIDENT
OF THIS BOARD AARON PESKIN AS WELL AS FORMER ASSEMBLYMAN
AND FORMER PRESIDENT OF THIS BOARD AND CURRENT CITY ATTORNEY
ATTORNEY DAVID DUKE. SO SOMETHING IS UP THAT
DISTRICT SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
COLLEAGUES ON THE OCCASION OF HER RETIREMENT I HAVE THE GREAT
HONOR TODAY OF RECOGNIZING A REMARKABLE PUBLIC SERVANT WHO
HAPPENS ALSO TO BE A FRIEND AND FORMER CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE COLLEAGUE OF MINE WHOSE CAREER HAS BEEN DISTINGUISHED
BY EXTRAORDINARY LEADERSHIP AND BY A FIERCE COMMITMENT TO
JUSTICE AND EQUITY. KUMIKO BURTON CAN WE TAKE THE
LECTERN? >> KUMIKO IS A PROUD SAN
FRANCISCAN, A GRADUATE OF LOWELL HIGH SCHOOL, UC DAVIS,
UC HASTINGS. NOW YOU SEE YOU SEE LAU SAN
FRANCISCO AND SOMEONE WHO HAS SPENT MORE THAN THREE DECADES
FIGHTING EFFECTIVELY AND WELL FOR OUR CITY'S MOST
DISADVANTAGED TO THOSE OF US WHO KNOW KIMMIE, OF COURSE
THAT'S NO SURPRISE SHE COMES FROM A FAMILY WHOSE COMMITMENT
TO PUBLIC SERVANT SERVICE IS LEGENDARY INCLUDING HER FATHER
JOHN BURTON, WHO'S HERE TODAY AS YOU MENTIONED, AN
EXTRAORDINARY ASSEMBLY MEMBER SENATOR SENATE PRESIDENT,
CONGRESSMAN CHAIR OF THE CALIFORNIA DEMOCRATIC PARTY
AND NOT LEAST THE EXTRAORDINARY FATHER WHO INSTILLED IN HIS NO
LESS EXTRAORDINAIRE EVERY DAUGHTER A PASSION FOR JUSTICE
AND A TIRELESS DRIVE TO FIGHT FOR THOSE WHO ARE VULNERABLE
AND MOST IN NEED OF FIGHTERS. KUMIKO BURTON JOINED THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE 22 YEARS AGO NOT LONG AFTER I JOINED THAT
OFFICE. IN FACT AS TEAM LEADER OF THE
CHILD AND FAMILY TEAM. NOW THE DEPENDENCY AND MENTAL
HEALTH TEAM SHE HAS LED THAT TEAM'S VITALLY IMPORTANT WORK
EVER SINCE OVERSEEING TWO CONFIDENTIAL COURT BASED
PRACTICES WITH VERY HEAVY AND ACTIVE COURT CASELOADS.
IT IS WORK THAT IS NEVER IN THE LIMELIGHT AND ITS HEROES ARE
ALWAYS UNSUNG. >> KIMMY'S TEAM HANDLED
CASELOADS THAT ROUTINELY INVOLVE SOME OF THE MOST
COMPLEX CASES AND MANY OF THE MOST DIFFICULT ISSUES KNOWN
IN HUMAN ENDEAVOR REPRESENTING THE INTERESTS OF ABUSED
AND NEGLECTED CHILDREN WORKING WITH PROTECTIVE SERVICES
WORKERS IN HANDLING MENTAL HEALTH CONSERVATORSHIPS
AND CARE COURT KIMI AND HER TEAM ADVISE THE FAMILIES
AND CHILDREN'S SERVICES DIVISION OF THE HUMAN SERVICES
AGENCY IN ALL PHASES OF DEPENDENCY LITIGATION AND IT'S
A TEAM THAT SERVES AS ADVICE COUNSEL AS WELL AS LITIGATION
COUNSEL ON MORE THAN 600 CONSERVATORSHIP CASES IN SAN
FRANCISCO, KIMI HAS GUIDED THAT WORK TIRELESSLY WITH COMPASSION
,HUMANITY AND PROFESSIONALISM AND A STEADY HAND APPEARING
IN COURT NEARLY EVERY DAY DURING THE PANDEMIC LEADING HER
TEAM THROUGH MAJOR SYSTEM CHANGES AND PREPARING FOR
AND IMPLEMENTING THE MOST SIGNIFICANT UPDATE TO
CALIFORNIA'S CONSERVATORSHIP LAWS IN MORE THAN 50 YEARS.
BEYOND HER LEGAL ACUMEN, HOWEVER, KIMIKO HAS ALSO BEEN A
POWERFUL FORCE FOR EQUITY WITHIN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE FOR THE PAST TWO YEARS SHE SERVED AS THE RACIAL EQUITY
ON THE RACIAL EQUITY TASK FORCE FIRST AS A MEMBER DENNIS
CO-CHAIR HELPING LEAD NEW INITIATIVES LIKE THAT OFFICE'S
LAW FELLOW PROGRAM AND ITS INTERNSHIP PARTNERSHIP WITH
HOWARD UNIVERSITY SCHOOL OF LAW.
SHE HAS ALSO BEEN AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE ASIAN PACIFIC
AMERICAN ALLIANCE SINCE ITS FOUNDING IN 2021 HELPING TO
STRENGTHEN THE COMMUNITY INVISIBILITY FOR AAPI STAFF.
>> KIMMY'S COLLEAGUES DESCRIBE HER AS A FIERCE ADVOCATE, A
THOUGHTFUL MENTOR, A SUPPORTIVE LEADER AND SOMEONE WHO BRINGS
HUMOR AND HEART TO EVERY SPACE SHE'S IN FURTHER ENHANCING MY
AFFECTION FOR HER. SHE'S ALSO A DIE HARD FAN OF
THE 40 NINERS AND TWO OF MY HIGHEST PROFILE CONSTITUENTS
OUR GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS AND YOUR SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS
AND OUR GOLDEN STATE BALCO. >> THAT'S RIGHT AND THE
VALKYRIES KUMIKO BURTON ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, IT IS MY HONOR TO COMMEND YOU FOR YOUR
YEARS OF SERVICE TO OUR CITY FOR BRINGING HOPE WHERE THERE
IS HOPELESSNESS, FOR GIVING VOICE TO THE VOICELESS, FOR
DOING JUSTICE AND FOR MAKING OURS A CITY THAT IS TRULY THE
CITY OF ST FRANCIS. WE THANK YOU AND WE
CONGRATULATE YOU ON YOUR WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT.
IF I MIGHT JUST ADD AN EXPRESSION OF GRATITUDE TO
KIMIKO BURTON I HAVE HAD THE GREAT GOOD FORTUNE OF BEING
ABLE TO WORK WITH YOU OVER MY LAST SEVEN YEARS ON THIS BOARD
WHERE I HAVE BEEN INTERESTED IN THE AREAS WHERE YOU HAVE
BEEN PRACTICING IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AND YOU HAVE
HAD THE MISFORTUNE OF PRACTICING AN AREA IN AN AREA
WHERE SO MANY POLITICIANS HAVE HAD SO MANY DEMANDS OVER THAT
TIME AND YOU HAVE CARRIED ON GRACEFULLY AND CONSISTENT WITH
THE LAW AND AND TRIED TO EXPLAIN TO POLITICIANS
AND OTHERS WHO MAY NOT ALWAYS UNDERSTAND WHAT THE LAW
REQUIRES, WHAT IT DOES REQUIRE AND ALSO EXPLAIN SOME OF THE
CHALLENGES ABOUT ACTUALLY MAKING PROGRESS IN SOME OF
THESE REALLY HARD AREAS. SO YOU ARE AS SUPERVISOR DORSEY
SAID, FUNNY AND CHARMING AND A GREAT LAWYER AND IT'S BEEN AN
HONOR TO BE ABLE TO WORK WITH YOU AND IT LOOKS LIKE YOU'RE
BOSS MIGHT WANT TO SAY SOMETHING FOR FORMER BOSS
FORMER BOSS FRIDAY DAVID YOU OKAY?
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISORS, WE APPRECIATE YOU TAKING A MOMENT TO ACKNOWLEDGE
AN INCREDIBLE HONOREE OUR SAN FRANCISCO CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE HAS BEEN BLESSED TO HAVE LEGIONS OF AMAZING LEGAL
PROFESSIONALS WHO HAVE GRACED OUR OFFICE AND OUR CITY
GOVERNMENT. >> BUT AS I'VE SAID AT NOW,
SEVERAL RETIREMENT CELEBRATIONS WHEN KIMI BURTON STARTED WITH
THE CITY SHE BROKE THE MOLD AS SHE LEAVES THE CITY SHE HAS
SHATTERED THE MOLD WITH A FEW F-BOMBS IN BETWEEN.
>> SOME 34 YEARS AGO AS SUPERVISOR DORSEY HAS LAID OUT
,SHE STARTED SERVING OUR CITY AND LIKE BURDENS BEFORE HER
INCLUDING THE INCREDIBLE 92 YEAR OLD BURTON WHO IS GRACING
OUR PRESENCE TODAY. SHE HAS GIVEN VOICE TO THE
VOICELESS. SHE HAS FOUGHT FOR THE MOST
VULNERABLE AMONG US WHETHER IT BE COUNTLESS INDIVIDUALS FACING
CRIMINAL CHARGES. WHEN SHE WAS A DEPUTY PUBLIC
DEFENDER OR HER WORK ON BEHALF OF HUNDREDS OF CHILDREN
IN CHILD ABUSE AND NEGLECT CASES OR COUNTLESS UNHOUSED
INDIVIDUALS OR INDIVIDUALS WITH MENTAL HEALTH CHALLENGES.
SHE HAS SERVED IN OUR OFFICE AS THE HEAD OF OUR CHILD
AND FAMILY TEAM AND THE HEAD OF OUR MENTAL HEALTH
AND DEPENDENCY TEAM LEADING HER TEAM AND OUR OFFICE THROUGH
MANY MANY CHANGES IN THE LAW OVER THE DECADES REFORMS IN OUR
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM, IMPLEMENTING OUR NEW CARE COURT
SYSTEM, PREPARING FOR INCREDIBLE UPDATES TO OUR
CONSERVATORSHIP LAW AND OVER THE YEARS SHE HAS SERVED NOT
JUST THOUSANDS OF SAN FRANCISCANS BUT SHE HAS GUIDED
DOZENS AND DOZENS OF INCREDIBLE LEGAL PROFESSIONALS THROUGH
THEIR WORK. AND I SPEAK ON THEIR BEHALF.
SHE'S BEEN AN INCREDIBLE MENTOR AND A MODEL FOR LEGIONS OF
PUBLIC SERVANTS AND IF THAT IS NOT ENOUGH, SHE IS SOMEONE WHO
HAS BEEN A CHAMPION FOR EQUITY AND OPPORTUNITY WITHIN OUR
OFFICE AND OUR CITY AS OUR OKCOIN CHAIR OF OUR RACIAL
EQUITY TASK FORCE. >> THERE IS NO ONE WHO HAS BEEN
A MORE FIERCE OR STRATEGIC ADVOCATE FOR THE CAUSES THAT
SHE HAS LED. THERE'S NO ONE WHO HAS A BIGGER
HEART AND THERE IS NO ONE WHO IS SASSIER.
>> AND SO ON BEHALF OF THE BEST MUNICIPAL LAW OFFICE IN THE
COUNTRY AS WE LOSE ONE OF THE VERY BEST OF OUR RANKS, WE WANT
TO WISH HER THE VERY BEST AS SHE STARTS A NEW PHASE IN HER
LIFE. OUR BEST TO YOU.
WE LOVE YOU KIMI BURTON EUROPE .
>> MACKAY HE SAID I CAN'T SWEAR I HAVE BEEN CALLED TO THE
PRINCIPAL'S OFFICE. MATT SUPER SUPERVISOR DARCY
SORRY. THANK YOU SO MUCH AND TO ALL OF
THE MEMBERS OF THIS AUGUST BOARD AND ANGELA I REMEMBER
WHEN WE WERE BABY CITY EMPLOYEES TOGETHER AND GIRL
LOOK AT YOU NOW AND THANK YOU RAFAEL AND EVERYONE SHOUT OUT
TO MY SUPERVISOR SHIMON THE BIGGEST SHOUT OUT TO MY FAMILY
MY MOM COULDN'T BE HERE AND MY SON IS WORKING BUT MY DAUGHTER
AND MY DAD ARE HERE AND WITHOUT MY FAMILY NONE OF THIS WOULD BE
POSSIBLE. >> THEY HAVE WORN THE
SACRIFICES THEY HAVE BORNE AND SACRIFICE AS I HAVE DONE MY
WORK OVER THE LAST 34 YEARS. SO FOR THAT I AM GRATEFUL.
>> I ALSO NEED TO GIVE MY MOM A SHOUT OUT.
EVERYBODY TALKS ABOUT THE BURTON LEGACY WHICH IS AMAZING
BUT I COME FROM IT ON BOTH SIDES.
MY GRANDFATHER ON MY MOM'S SIDE WAS A LABOR ORGANIZER WHEN IT
WAS VERY UNPOPULAR TO BE A LABOR ORGANIZER AND ONE GOT
THROWN INTO PRISON FOR SUCH THINGS WHICH MY GRANDFATHER DID
. SO I COME FROM IT ON BOTH
SIDES. I AM A BURTON, I AM A HALL
AND I AM AN OGAWA AND I AM PROUD OF ALL OF THAT.
>> I'M DAVID. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
KEEPING ME WHEN YOU CAME WHEN YOU CAME ON WE HAVEN'T HAD AS
MANY YEARS BUT IT HAS BEEN A WONDERFUL RIDE WITH YOU SO
THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND THE WAY THAT YOU RUN THIS
OFFICE. >> SHOUT OUT TO YVONNE MARIE I
DON'T EVEN KNOW WHAT YOUR TITLE IS BUT WHATEVER IT IS THE BEST
ONE IN MY VIEW THAT THE OFFICE HAS EVER HAD SHE OUR TEAM DOES
WORK THAT AS MATT SAID IN RAPHINHA'S DON'T HIT THE
HEADLINES UNLESS SOMETHING REALLY REALLY BAD HAS HAPPENED.
>> SO WE DO LIKE TO STAY OUT OF THE PAPER BUT YVONNE HAS THROWN
HERSELF INTO BECOMING FAMILIAR WITH THE WORK THAT WE DO AND IS
SUCH A TREMENDOUS SUPPORT TO MY TEAM FORMER TEAM AND I KNOW HOW
MUCH SHE WILL SUPPORT DIANA CARBAJAL STRAIGHT WHO WAS HERE
IN THE AUDIENCE WHO IS HAS TAKEN OVER THE LEADERSHIP OF
THIS REMARKABLE TEAM AND I JUST SO MUCH OF MY TEAM IS HERE
TODAY AND I THANK YOU GUYS SO MUCH FOR BEING HERE.
>> I KNOW YOU GUYS DON'T EVEN ALL COME IN ON TUESDAYS SO
THANK YOU FOR COMING IN FOR THAT AND TO I SEE A NUMBER OF
MY COLLEAGUES, MY FORMER COLLEAGUE JULIE THANK YOU BUT
THANK YOU EVERYBODY FOR BEING HERE.
>> CHRIS SHOUT OUT CO CHAIR OF HIPAA.
THANK YOU FOR THE WORK THAT YOU CONTINUE TO DO FOR THE CITY
AND FOR THE WORK THAT OUR TEAM DOES THAT IS LARGELY UNKNOWN
AND UNDER THE RADAR AS IT SHOULD BE.
BUT YOU GUYS DO REMARKABLE WORK.
NEVER FORGET THAT. NEVER FORGET THAT YOU ARE KICK
ATTORNEYS THAT YOU GUYS CAN CARRY ANYBODY'S WATER AND COURT
AND THAT I WOULD COME TO YOU GUYS WITH ANY LEGAL PROBLEM
AND WANT YOU GUYS TO BE THE ONE CARRYING MY BAG THERE'S OTHER
WORDS THAT COME TO MIND. >> I'M TRYING TO BE TRYING TO
BEHAVE. >> ANYWAY, THANK YOU SO MUCH.
I REALLY APPRECIATE THIS HONOR. I'M GOING TO STOP TALKING.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. YOU CAN OPEN UP TO WANT TO GET
TO OKAY. >> NEXT UP DISTRICT NINE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESENT AMENDMENT COLLEAGUES
TODAY I HAVE THE DISTINCT PLEASURE OF HONORING MY DEAR
FRIENDS AND DINA AND THE SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS CHARLIE
AND CHRISSIE HARB OWNERS OF CHARLIE'S CAFE.
>> PLEASE COME TO THE PODIUM. >> CHARLIE'S CAFE HAS BEEN A
BELOVED FIXTURE IN BERNAL HEIGHTS THAT HAS BEEN
IN OPERATION FOR OVER 24 YEARS. IT'S BEEN A CENTRAL GATHERING
SPOT ON THE PROCEEDINGS PARK SIDE OF BERNAL HEIGHTS SINCE
2001 BEFORE THE CAFE CAME INTO BEING IN 1989, CHRISTIE DROVE
ACROSS THE COUNTRY FROM HER HOMETOWN OF DETROIT TO LIVE
IN SAN FRANCISCO WITH HER BROTHER AND ATTEND CITY
COLLEGE. >> A NATIVE OF PALESTINE,
CHARLIE ATTENDED BETHLEHEM UNIVERSITY AS AN UNDERGRAD
AND WENT ON TO GRADUATE SCHOOL FOR ARCHITECTURE IN JERUSALEM
WHEN THE UPRISING OF 1987 BROKE OUT.
THE RESULTING POLITICAL TURMOIL AND DANGEROUS ROAD CLOSURES
AND BLOCKADES FORCED CHARLIE TO LEAVE HIS STUDIES IN JERUSALEM
AND EARN HIS DEGREE IN ARCHITECTURE FROM UC
BERKELEY. CHARLIE MET HIS WIFE AND LIFE
PARTNER CHRISSY IN 1991. THEIR TWO WONDERFUL KIDS DALIA
AND JERRY'S GREW UP IN THE CAFE.
IN 2001 CHARLIE BOUGHT A LITTLE CORNER BUSINESS WITH HIS SISTER
AIDA, WHO WAS PLANNING TO RUN A CAFE WITH HER HUSBAND SHORTLY
AFTER PURCHASE RATHER THAN PREGNANT WITH HER THIRD CHILD,
DECIDED TO MOVE HER FAMILY TO CANADA AND LEFT THE BUSINESS
IN THE HANDS OF CHRISTY AND CHARLIE WHO ESTABLISHED
WHAT WAS WHAT HAS BECOME A REGULAR STOP FOR HUNDREDS OF
NEIGHBORS FROM THROUGHOUT BERNAL AND THE MISSION THESE
NEIGHBORS ALL CALLED CHARLIE AND CHRISSIE.
THEY'RE GOOD FRIENDS BECAUSE ONCE YOU ENTER THEIR DOOR YOU
ARE BROUGHT IMMEDIATELY INTO THEIR ORBIT OF FRIENDSHIP
AND TODAY YOU CAN SEE THAT IN ACTION WITH THE GROUP FROM
THE NEIGHBORHOOD THAT HAS COME TO CHEER THEM ON OVER THE YEARS
. >> OVER THE YEARS THEY HAVE
AMASSED A BROAD DEDICATED COMMUNITY WHO ADORE THEM, SOME
OF WHOM ARE HERE AND OVER THE YEARS CHARLIE HAS EMPLOYED A
WIDE DIVERSITY OF PEOPLE WHO COME FROM ALL OVER THE WORLD.
THE CURRENT STAFF ARE RARELY CHRISTINA JO SAY AND ALEXI
CONTRIBUTES SO MUCH TO MAKING THE CAFÉ WARM AND WELCOMING ON
ANY GIVEN DAY THEY CAN BE FOUND WORKING BEHIND THE COUNTER,
JUGGLING MULTIPLE ORDERS, PREPARING THE FOOD AND ALWAYS
TREATING EACH CUSTOMER WITH A BIG SMILE.
>> WHAT SETS WHAT SETS THIS PLACE APART FROM OTHERS IS THE
SENSE OF FAMILIARITY AND JOY AND COMMUNITY.
WHEN YOU WALK IN THE DOOR. CHARLIE AND CHRISTY HAVE
DEDICATED THEMSELVES TO CREATING A SPACE THAT IS AN
EXPRESSION OF LOVE FOR THE COMMUNITY AND THEY CONTINUE TO
DO THIS DESPITE THE DIFFICULTIES OF KEEPING A SMALL
BUSINESS AFLOAT IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THROUGH THE YEARS THEY HAVE HOSTED EVENTS THAT ELEVATE
IMPORTANT SOCIAL ISSUES AND PROMOTE ART, POETRY
AND MUSIC. THEY HOST CULTURAL CELEBRATIONS
AND FUNDRAISERS FOR PALESTINE, UKRAINE AND ALL MANNER OF LOCAL
AND GLOBAL ISSUES. DURING THE PANDEMIC THEY OPENED
A PARKLET AND HELD OUTDOOR LIVE BLUEGRASS JAMS ON FRIDAY
MORNINGS AND WEEKENDS THAT CONTINUED TO THIS DAY INCLUDING
A THURSDAY NIGHT POP UP AS WELL AS A POP UP ON FRIDAY MORNINGS.
>> WHETHER IT'S HELPING BUILD CONNECTIONS AMONG NEIGHBORS OR
JUST OFFERING A RELAXING PLACE TO HANG OUT AND HAVE A BITE
CHARLIE'S CAFE IS ALWAYS THERE. >> I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU ALL
FOR BEING SUCH A PILLAR IN THE COMMUNITY AND FOR ALL YOU DO
FOR DISTRICT NINE THAT GIVES YOU A RIGHT FIELDER.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT AND BOARD MEMBERS.
>> I JUST WANTED TO ANNOUNCE THAT YOU'RE RETIRING TOO SINCE
IT LOOKS LIKE EVERYBODY BEFORE US RETIRED.
>> MAYBE WE KEEP UP THE SAME THEME.
>> WE'RE VERY HUMBLED ESPECIALLY WITH THE PREVIOUS
PEOPLE WHO ARE AHEAD OF US. WE FEEL LIKE WE'RE WE'RE JUST
LIVING OUR LIFESTYLE AND WE'RE DOING OUR NORMAL LIFE.
>> IT'S SO I DON'T THINK RUNNING A SMALL BUSINESS
FRANCISCO IS A BUSINESS. I FEEL LIKE IT'S JUST A
CULTURE. IT'S A WAY OF LIFE.
YOU SPEND TEN HOURS A DAY, SEVEN DAYS A WEEK AMONG THESE
PEOPLE. >> WE'RE VERY HONORED TO WHAT
WE DO. CHRISTIANI, 24 YEARS OLD,
WORKED DAY AND NIGHT. >> IN THE BEGINNING IT'S VERY
HARD BUT WE MADE IT HAPPEN. >> I MEAN LIKE I SAID, WE HAVE
A HUGE FAMILY. I MEAN WE HAVE THOUSANDS OF
PEOPLE WE CONSIDER VERY CLOSE FRIENDS AND FEW PEOPLE ARE HERE
BUT EVERYONE MAKES A DIFFERENCE TO US AND MAKE US GET UP AT
6:00 IN THE MORNING AND OPEN UP AND WAIT FOR A SMILE OR
SOMEBODY TO COME AND CHECK ON US.
ESPECIALLY IN THE LAST FEW YEARS FOR WHAT'S HAPPENING
IN THE OLD COUNTRY. EVERYBODY COMES IN WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE A DAY COME AND CHECK ON
MY MOM AND MY BROTHER AND MY FAMILY.
SO WE FEEL WE'RE PART OF THE CITY.
I'VE BEEN HERE 35 YEARS AND AS AN IMMIGRANT I DON'T FEEL AS AN
IMMIGRANT AT ALL COMPARED TO EVERYBODY AROUND THE CENTER.
CISCO IS VERY SPECIAL. IT'S REALLY I NEVER LEFT IT
PEOPLE. >> AND HOW COME YOU NEVER TRIED
SOMEWHERE ELSE LIKE BECAUSE THIS IS HOME NOW.
>> WE THANK YOU. MY EXTENDED FAMILY MY MOM'S
FAMILY CAME HERE IN THE 70S AND MY GREAT UNCLES CAME HERE
IN THE 60S AND THEY NEVER LEFT EITHER.
>> I MEAN IT'S A PLACE TO BE COMFORTABLE AS A FOREIGNER JUST
TO MAKE IT HOME. WE REALLY APPRECIATE THIS HONOR
AND WE'RE HUMBLED TO HAVE IT. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
IS IT STILL ON? I JUST WANT TO THANK ALL OF YOU
GUYS FOR BEING HERE AND SUPPORTING US FOR SO MANY
YEARS. >> PROJECT
BASED AND THAT'S ANOTHER. >> ALL RIGHT.
AND FINALLY FROM DISTRICT EIGHT, I AM GOING TO INVITE
DEBBIE LEHRMAN TO COME ON UP. >> COLLEAGUES, TODAY IT IS MY
HONOR TO PRESENT A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO DEBBIE LEHRMAN
WHO EARLIER THIS YEAR RETIRED AFTER MORE THAN TWO DECADES AS
THE DIRECTOR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO HUMAN SERVICES
NETWORK AND A 40 YEAR CAREER OF ADVOCACY COMMUNITY ORGANIZING
AND PUBLIC SERVICE. SINCE 2001, DEBBIE LED THE
HUMAN SERVICES NETWORK, A COALITION OF NEARLY 80
NONPROFIT HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICE PROVIDERS THAT SERVE
THOUSANDS OF SAN FRANCISCANS EVERY DAY.
UNDER HER DIRECTION, THE NETWORK HAS BECOME ONE OF THE
MOST TRUSTED VOICES FOR THE CITY'S SAFETY NET ADVOCATE FOR
FAIR FUNDING, EFFECTIVE POLICY AND A MORE EQUITABLE
PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN GOVERNMENT AND THE NONPROFIT SECTOR.
>> SHE'S GUIDED THE COALITION THROUGH MULTIPLE BUDGET CRISES,
DEFENDED CRITICAL SERVICES FROM CUTS AND HELPED SHAPED THE
VALUES THAT NOW ANCHOR SAN FRANCISCO'S HUMAN SERVICES
FUNDING FRAMEWORK. IN EVERY MEETING, EVERY
HEARING, EVERY HALLWAY CONVERSATION AND CITY HALL,
DEBBIE HAS SHOWN UP RELENTLESS PREPARED AND ALWAYS GROUNDED
IN THE NEEDS OF THOSE MOST IMPACTED.
>> BEFORE JOINING THE NETWORK, DEBBIE SERVED IN A RANGE OF
LEADERSHIP ROLES THAT REFLECT HER COMMITMENT TO ECONOMIC
JUSTICE AND OPPORTUNITY. FROM PLACING LOW INCOME WORKERS
INTO GOOD UNION CONSTRUCTION JOBS TO MANAGING COALITIONS
FOCUSED ON ENVIRONMENTAL AND HEALTH EQUITY, TO RAISING
FUNDS AND BUILDING CAPACITY FOR COUNTLESS LOCAL NONPROFITS.
>> A PROUD ALUM OF M.I.T. AND UC BERKELEY SCHOOL OF LAW
GABEL WAS. DEBBIE BROUGHT RIGOR STRATEGY
AND A SENSE OF PURPOSE TO EVERY ROLE SHE HELD.
SHE'S ALSO BEEN A TIRELESS VOLUNTEER AN ORGANIZER RAISING
MONEY FOR FRONTLINE ORGANIZATIONS, COUNSELING
STUDENTS IN CRISIS AND WORKING THE FLOOR AT SAN FRANCISCO'S
ICONIC MUSIC VENUES FOR DECADES AS A VOLUNTEER USHER
AND SUPERVISOR. THROUGHOUT HER CAREER, DEBBIE
HAS COMBINED SHARP POLICY ANALYSIS WITH GRASSROOTS
SENSIBILITY. NEVER LOSING SIGHT OF THE
PEOPLE BEHIND THE PROGRAMS. SHE'S BEEN A STEADY CHAMPION
FOR NONPROFIT WORKERS FOR BETTER CONTRACTING PRACTICES
AND FOR A CITY THAT INVESTS IN THE PEOPLE AND ORGANIZATIONS
THAT HOLD OUR SOCIAL FABRIC TOGETHER.
HER IMPACT HAS BEEN FELT IN NEARLY EVERY HUMAN SERVICES
BUDGET THE CITY HAS PASSED OVER THE LAST 20 YEARS.
ON BEHALF OF A GRATEFUL CITY, THANK YOU DEBBIE, FOR YOUR
PASSION, YOUR PERSISTENCE, YOUR INCREDIBLE MIND AND YOUR
LIFELONG COMMITMENT TO MAKING SAN FRANCISCO A MORE JUST
AND COMPASSIONATE PLACE. CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR VERY
WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT AND NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR THIS HONOR.
>> IT IS VERY MEANINGFUL TO ME. I WAS VERY NERVOUS THE FIRST
TIME I CAME UP TO THIS PODIUM ALMOST 25 YEARS AGO AND I'M A
LITTLE NERVOUS NOW. >> WELL, DEBBIE, WE WANT TO
HEAR YOU BETTER SO GRAB THAT MICROPHONE CLOSER TO YOU,
PLEASE. >> GOT IT.
ANGELA, THANK YOU. ONE OF THE FIRST THINGS I DID
FOR THE HUMAN SERVICES NETWORK WAS ORGANIZE A CONFERENCE ON
THIS THE THREE LEGGED STOOL THE PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN NONPROFITS,
GOVERNMENT AND THE PHILANTHROPIC SECTOR.
AND TODAY IT FEELS LIKE THAT PARTNERSHIP'S A LITTLE SHAKY.
WE HAVE SOME HUGE BUDGET CUTS POLITICAL ATTACKS COMING FROM
WELL MONEYED INTERESTS AND A FEDERAL GOVERNMENT THAT IS
MAKING THE ACT OF HELPING PEOPLE ALMOST SUBVERSIVE.
AND IT IS SHOCKING WHAT WE'RE GOING THROUGH TODAY.
>> I WOULD BE REMISS IF I DIDN'T MENTION THE COST OF
DOING BUSINESS TODAY. >> I HAVE I'VE USED THAT PHRASE
SO MANY TIMES THAT I'VE THOUGHT ABOUT TRAINING A PARROT TO JUST
SIT ON MY SHOULDER AND SAY IT OVER AND OVER AGAIN UNTIL IT
SINKS IN. >> NONPROFITS ARE A TREASURE.
>> YOU DON'T KNOW WHAT IT'S GOT TILL IT'S GONE AND THE CITY
MUST RENEW ITS COMMITMENT TO SUSTAINING OUR NONPROFITS TO
PREVENT UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCE THIS AND HARM TO THE PEOPLE
THAT WE SERVE. AND MOST IMPORTANT I THANK
EVERY FRONT LINE WORKER WHO HAS THE HARDEST JOB IN THE CITY
GETTING UP IN THE MORNING AND GOING OUT THERE TO HELP
PEOPLE. >> THEY DESERVE BETTER WAGES.
>> I CAN SPEAK PERSONALLY WHAT IT'S LIKE TO HAVE A 45 YEAR
CAREER IN THE NONPROFIT SECTOR. I'VE BEEN ABLE TO GET AWAY WITH
IT BECAUSE I HAVE A RENT CONTROLLED APARTMENT.
I HAVE CATS INSTEAD OF KIDS AND YEAH, I HAVE A SECOND JOB.
>> I DO SECURITY AT THE FILLMORE SO I CAN GO SEE LIVE
MUSIC THAT I CAN'T AFFORD ON A NONPROFIT SALARY.
AND IT'S NOT RIGHT TO ASK THAT OF OTHERS WHO WANT TO HAVE A
SIMILAR CAREER PATH. SO WE NEED TO REMAIN LASER
FOCUSED ON THAT GOAL. SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN A
LEADER AND HAS ALWAYS AND WILL CONTINUE TO MAKE NATIONAL
CHANGE BY OUR EXAMPLE. AND SO EVERYTHING YOU DO
IN THIS ROOM IS IMPORTANT. IT HAS BEEN MY PRIVILEGE TO BE
A PART OF THAT AS AN ADVOCATE FOR OUR SECTOR AND TO HELP
EMPOWER OTHERS TO FILL THAT ROLE AS WELL.
AND I HAVE THE DEEPEST GRATITUDE TO ALL OF OUR
NONPROFITS. THEIR LEADERS AND THEIR WORKERS
TO THE HUMAN SERVICES NETWORK'S FOUNDERS BRUCE FISHER AND ANNE
LAZARUS WHO HIRED ME 24 YEARS AGO AND TO OUR CO-CHAIRS STEVE
FIELDS AND SHERRILYN ADAMS WHO GIVE SO MUCH OF THEIR TIME TO
HSN WHILE STRUGGLING TO RUN THEIR OWN HUGE ORGANIZATIONS.
AND TO OUR NEW LEADER ROCIO MOLINA WHO IF YOU HAVEN'T MET
HER YET YOU'RE YOU'RE GOING TO AND HAVE EVERY CONFIDENCE
IN HER ABILITY TO TAKE ON THIS NEXT PHASE OF HER SENSE WORK.
I THANK MY PARTNER JOEL GENDLER FOR SUPPORTING ME.
>> I COULDN'T DO THIS WORK WITHOUT HIM AND I THINK EVERY
PUBLIC OFFICIAL DEPARTMENT HEAD SUPERVISOR, MAYOR'S OFFICE
STAFF PERSON, LEGISLATIVE STAFF ANGELA ALL OF YOU WHO HAVE
STOOD UP FOR OUR SECTOR AND WHO HAVE SUPPORTED BETTER FUNDING,
BETTER SERVICES AND BETTER PAY FOR OUR WORKERS AND OVER THE
YEARS EVEN THE ONES WHO EVEN WHEN WE'VE DISAGREED I HAVE TO
SAY THAT MOST HAVE ENGAGED IN CONVERSATIONS WITH RESPECT
AND SUBSTANCE AND THOUGHTFULNESS AND I VERY
MUCH APPRECIATE THAT. >> SO AGAIN, THANK YOU
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN THANK YOU TO THE WHOLE BOARD.
SHOUT OUT TO DISTRICT ONE MY HOME FOR 35 YEARS AND OUR GREAT
SUPERVISOR CONNIE CHAN. >> I'M SURE THIS WILL NOT BE
THE LAST YOU HEAR FROM ME. >> SO THANK YOU
. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO I THINK THAT TAKES US BACK TO PUBLIC COMMENTS.
>> YES. FOR THOSE OF YOU WHO STILL
WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT, PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR
RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER WILL SET THE TIME FOR TWO
MINUTES. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
SPEAKER. IS THAT YOU, MR. ALLMAN?
>> OKAY. WELCOME.
>> YEAH. THANK YOU, ANGELA.
THE LAST TIME I TALKED TO YOU BOTH AND IN THIS BILL THIS I
THINK I WAS IN THE CLERK'S OFFICE YOU WERE SAYING TOM
AMMIANO. IS THAT CORRECT?
YOU'RE HAVING DINNER WITH THEM OR SOMETHING?
>> IS THAT CORRECT? YES, BUT MR. ALMOND, THIS IS
YOUR TIME TO TALK TO THE BOARD ABOUT YOUR THOUGHTS.
>> YES. I DON'T KNOW SEMIANNUAL MET OR
SEE CONNIE CHAN YOU? I DON'T KNOW HOW TO SAY YOUR
NAME, SIR. TO THE BOARD AS A WHOLE.
>> THIS GENTLEMAN AFRICAN-AMERICAN GENTLEMAN?
YES. CONNIE CHAN THE JET.
MY NEW SUPERVISOR. I DON'T KNOW HIS NAME.
HE HE SAID IT TO ME. I HEAR IT SEVERAL TIMES.
MS.. MELGAR.
AND OF COURSE HE AMENDMENT AND I NEED TO COME HERE MORE
OFTEN FOR YOUR COMMITTEE MEMBERSHIP.
I WANT TO APOLOGIZE TO SUPERVISOR RAFI AMENDMENT.
LAST WEEK WELL FIRST I WENT TO THE BOARD OF ELECTIONS.
I THINK IT WAS WEDNESDAY. I CAME TO SUPERVISOR RALPH
AMENDMENTS OFFICE. AND WHEN I ARRIVED THERE WAS A
WOMAN AND A MAN I DIDN'T FIND RIGHT AWAY.
THEY WERE INTERNS. A WOMAN CAME OUT OF THE
RESTROOM BECAUSE I THINK THE DOOR MIGHT HAVE BEEN CLOSED
AND SHE INTRODUCED HERSELF TO ME AND I GOT AN ARGUMENT WITH
HER AND HER NAME WAS MELANIE SOMETHING.
WHAT'S YOUR LAST NAME PLEASE? MELANIE.
THIS IS AN AIDE TO RALPH HERE AMENDMENT MELANIE.
SO A LEGISLATIVE AIDE I GOT AN ARGUMENT WITH HER AND SHE SAID
SHE GAVE $100 TO OH, NO, I'M NOT THROUGH.
I NEED TO SAY THIS PLACE. SO SHE GAVE $100 AND I SAID I
JUST MET YOU AND I DON'T BELIEVE YOU.
SO WE GOT INTO AN ARGUMENT AND SHE CALLED THE SHERIFFS
AND A WHOLE BUNCH SHOWED UP. I WAS SURPRISED BECAUSE SHE
DIDN'T LIKE MY ATTITUDE AND I GAVE HER ATTITUDE AND I'M
WRONG. SO WANT TO THANK YOU FOR ALL
THE WOMEN IN THIS CHAMBER. I DON'T KNOW ALL OF YOU BUT I
KNOW SOME OF YOU AND I WILL IN THE NEAR FUTURE COME TO THE
COMMITTEE MEMBERSHIP. BUT I'D LIKE TO INQUIRE.
I WANT TO APOLOGIZE TO RALPH FOR AMENDMENT AND STATE SENATOR
SCOTT WIENER AND I HAVE ONE OTHER.
THANK YOU, MR. RANDLEMAN. I WANT TO SAY ONE MORE THANK
YOU, SUPERVISOR. I GIVE TO THE THE JEFFREY.
>> JEFFREY YOUR TIME IS CONCLUDED.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. CAN WE HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE? SORRY.
THANK YOU. OKAY.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. YOU'RE WELCOME.
THANK YOU FOR ALL YOUR TIME EVERY ONE OF YOU AND THIS WHOLE
ROOM. >> ALL RIGHT.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> OKAY.
HELLO. MY NAME IS LEAH MCGEEVER AND I
LIVE IN D6. >> DURING THE TRANS MARCH THE
MAYOR WAS HECKLED AWAY BECAUSE HE WAS NOT WELCOME THERE AND IT
WASN'T HIS EVENT. ON JUNE 28TH THE GENDER GAY
DISTRICT SUPERVISOR HAD THIS TO SAY TO HIS TRANSPHOBIC
CONSERVATIVE BASE. THIS OBNOXIOUS BEHAVIOR DOESN'T
REPRESENT SAN FRANCISCO'S LGBTQ COMMUNITY AND OUR ALLY
MAYOR DANIEL LAURIE DESERVES BETTER.
>> EVERYONE IN THE LGBT COMMUNITY NEEDS TO START
CALLING OUT THIS EMBARRASSING FRINGE THAT'S BADLY HURTING THE
CAUSE OF LGBTQ PLUS PROGRESS FOR ALL OF US.
TO ME THIS LITERALLY SOUNDS LIKE HE'S CALLING FOR PEOPLE TO
BULLY US. >> FOR WHAT?
DECORUM. NONE OF YOU REPRESENT THE
TRANSGENDER COMMUNITY YOU SHOULD BE SUPPORTING US BUT
YOU'RE NOT. >> SO SHUT THE UP ABOUT HOW
YOU THINK WE SHOULD BE PROTESTING OUR OPPRESSION, OUR
DEHUMANIZATION, OUR DEMONIZATION AND ERASURE FROM
SOCIETY. GOT THAT?
NONE OF YOU GAVE A SINGLE ABOUT THE TRANS FLAG BEING
TAKEN AWAY FROM THE PRIDE FLAG RAISING CEREMONY.
BLACK AND BROWN TRANS WOMEN FOUGHT FOR YOUR GAY RIGHTS.
>> AND ARE YOU GIVING ANY OF YOUR RIGHTS UP VOLUNTARILY
BECAUSE OF DECORUM, DECENCY? Y'ALL HAVE ABANDONED TRANS
CHILDREN AND YOUTH WHICH IS UNCONSCIONABLE.
THERE'S NOT ONE PRESS RELEASE OR STATEMENT ABOUT LIFESAVING
HEALTH CARE BEING TAKEN AWAY FROM CHILDREN IN THIS COUNTRY.
TRANS CHILDREN. >> HOW CAN YOU ABANDON THEM
KNOWING BECAUSE YOU THINK YOU KNOW THEM BETTER THAN
YOURSELVES. I MEAN YOU KNOW YOURSELF.
>> JUST OFF UNLESS YOU'RE GOING TO SUPPORT US.
DID I INDEED? THERE IS A DRAG ARTIST THE
LATIN NEXT ONE THAT WAS ABDUCTED LAST WEEK BY ICE.
>> ONE SUPERVISOR ACTUALLY SHOWED UP FOR AN EVENT TO
SUPPORT THAT PERSON. ANOTHER ONE SAID THEY'RE
KEEPING TABS ON IT AND EVERYONE ELSE IS SILENT, IS SAFE.
A TRANSGENDER AND IMMIGRANT SANCTUARY CITY ARE NOT.
AND YOU'LL BE FUNNY IF THIS MEXICAN STOLE YOUR JOB.
>> OH, LIAM MCGEEVER I'VE HEARD YOU MAKE SIMILAR COMMENTS BUT
BEING MORE ARTICULATE YOU HAVE YOU HAVE A GOOD SPEAKING
ABILITY. >> IF YOU ARE IN MY POSITION
WITH EVERYTHING THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> YOU WOULD UNDERSTAND. >> CAN WE HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE? GOOD AFTERNOON.
I WAS BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I'M A RENTER AND I'VE LIVED IN MY CURRENT HOME ON THE EDGE
OF NOMI VALLEY IN THE MISSION FOR OVER 20 YEARS.
I LOVE THIS CITY. I'VE ALWAYS BELIEVED IN ITS
VALUES BUT RIGHT NOW I FEEL COMPLETELY UNPROTECTED.
WE HEAR A LOT ABOUT TENANT PROTECTIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND RIGHTLY SO. BUT WHAT HAPPENS WHEN SOMEONE
WHO IS NEVER ON THE LEASE NEVER SCREENED AND NEVER APPROVED,
GAINED ACCESS TO A UNIT AND BEGINS TERRORIZING
ROOMMATES, THREATENING OTHER TENANTS, HARASSING NEIGHBORS,
DAMAGING PROPERTY AND VIOLATING COURT ORDERS?
WHAT HAPPENS WHEN THEIR BEHAVIOR DRIVES OUT LAWFUL
TENANTS AND DESTABILIZES ENTIRE BUILDINGS AND LEAVES NEIGHBORS
TO POLICE THEIR OWN SAFETY? WHAT ABOUT THE SMALL BUSINESS
OWNERS WHO HAVE POURED THEIR LIFE SAVINGS INTO THESE
PROPERTIES? THIS ISN'T A ONE TIME INCIDENT.
IN MY CASE THIS INDIVIDUAL HAS DONE THE SAME THING AT AT LEAST
FIVE OTHER PROPERTIES ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO AND I'M SURE
THERE ARE OTHERS LIKE HIM BAD ACTORS WHO EXPLOIT GAPS IN OUR
CITY LAWS. NOW IT'S HAPPENING AGAIN.
THIS TIME IN THE FLAT DIRECTLY BELOW ME I'VE GONE TO COURT.
I'VE OBTAINED BOTH A CIVIL HARASSMENT RESTRAINING ORDER
AND A CRIMINAL PROTECTIVE ORDER.
I'VE FILED REPORTS. I'VE CALLED 911 BUT THE POLICE
ARE STRETCHED SO THIN THEY OFTEN DON'T RESPOND AT ALL OR
THEY SHOW UP HOURS LATER WHEN THE DANGER HAS PASSED.
EVEN CLEAR VIOLATIONS OF COURT ORDERS ARE TREATED AS OPTIONAL.
THERE IS NO COORDINATED CITY RESPONSE, NO ACCOUNTABILITY, NO
SAFETY NET FOR LONG TIME RESIDENTS LIKE ME WHO ARE BEING
TERRORIZED IN OUR OWN HOMES. I'VE HAD TO MOVE MY DOGS TO
SAFETY. I'M CURRENTLY TAKING TIME OFF
WORK TO PACK UP MY LIFE NOT BECAUSE I WANT TO LEAVE BUT
BECAUSE I NO LONGER FEEL SAFE STAYING.
THIS IS A SYSTEMIC FAILURE. THERE ARE NO CITY RESOURCES FOR
MASTER TENANTS OR LONGTIME RESIDENTS TO TURN TO WHEN
THINGS GO OFF THE RAILS. AND YET WE'RE THE ONES LEFT
HOLDING THE BAG PAYING LAWYERS ,LOSING WAGES, CALLING 911
MANAGING TRAUMA AND FEARING FOR OUR SAFETY IN OUR OWN HOMES.
THIS IS NOT JUST A PERSONAL CRISIS OR HOUSING.
IT'S A FAILURE OF SERVICE. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR SHARING. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
YOU HAVE. YOU CAN LEAVE IT ON THE DAIS
THERE AND WE'LL PICK IT UP. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. YOU HAVE TWO MINUTES.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS ANN DRAPER AND I'M
STEPHANIE'S MOTHER. I OWN THE BUILDING SHE LIVES
IN AND PAYS RENT FOR. >> I HAVE AN UNLAWFUL DETAINER
PROCEEDING GOING AGAINST THIS INDIVIDUAL.
IT'S A NINE MONTH PROCESS. I WILL SEE IT THROUGH TO THE
END. HE'S ATTEMPTING TO EXTORT ME TO
PAY HIM MONEY TO LEAVE. BUT WHAT HE'S REALLY EXTORTING
ME FOR IS THE HARASSMENT OF FIVE WOMEN WHO LIVED IN MY
BUILDING. >> THREE OF THEM ARE GONE.
NONE OF THESE WOMEN DESERVE TO BE HARASSED AND THERE'S
SOMETHING YOU CAN DO ABOUT IT. YOU CAN TAKE A LOOK AT WHO IS
SLIPPING THROUGH THE CRACKS. A LOT OF THESE POLICIES
AND RENT ORDINANCES ARE A GOOD THING BUT THERE ARE ALWAYS
PEOPLE THAT CAN EVADE THEM AND AND GET AROUND THEM.
THREE ROOMMATES OF THIS INDIVIDUAL LEFT THE BUILDING
EACH IN A PANIC. AN ACCOUNTING ANALYST, A
PRESCHOOL TEACHER AND A WOMAN THAT TAKES CARE OF DOGS.
>> THESE ARE WOMEN THAT SHOULD HAVE BEEN SAFE LIVING IN A
UNIT. >> HE REMOVES ALL THE SMOKE
PROTECTORS WHO WON'T LET ME IN. ANYBODY IN THE BUILDING COULD
BE INJURED BY THAT AND AND EVERY WAY SO I LOOK, IT'S A
ROADBLOCK. >> I'M AN ATTORNEY.
I'M 76. I'M IN MY 50TH YEAR OF
PRACTICE. I SHOULD BE ABLE TO FIGURE THIS
OUT. >> HALF OF MY PRACTICE IS
IN DEPARTMENT 501 THE HOUSING COURT AND REAL PROPERTY
DEPARTMENT. BUT I CAN'T GET ANYTHING DONE
THAT PROTECTS MY TENANTS AND I HAVE A MORAL AND A LEGAL
OBLIGATION AND I WISH YOU WOULD DO SOMETHING.
>> FUND THE POLICE DEPARTMENT FOR THE MISSING 400 OFFICERS.
>> TAKE A LOOK AT WHO'S GETTING BY THESE.
THIS MAN HAS 21 CIVIL ACTIONS AND FIVE MORE UNDER ANOTHER
NAME AND 18 CIVIL RESTRAINING ORDERS.
HOW DOES THAT GET SLIPPING THROUGH THE SYSTEM?
I HOPE YOU'LL TAKE A LOOK AT IT.
>> IT WON'T SOLVE MY PROBLEM BUT IT'LL BE SOMEBODY ELSE'S.
THANK YOU. NEXT SPEAKER, PLEASE.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS MARK SOLOMON
AND I'VE LIVED IN WHAT WAS TO BECOME THE NATIVE CULTURAL
DISTRICT FOR 35 YEARS IN THE NORTH MISSION.
I CO-FOUNDED THE COMMUNITY LAND TRUST, SERVED ON THE MTA
CITIZEN ADVISORY COMMITTEE WROTE THE RESOLUTION THAT LED
TO THE HARVEY MILK MEMORIAL BEING PLACED HERE AND WAS A
MEMBER OF THE PLAZA 16 COALITION TEN YEARS AGO AS A
VOLUNTEER. >> OUR NEIGHBORHOOD HAS A
HISTORY. MISSION NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER 20
YEARS AGO WAS WELCOMED IN AS A HOMELESS CENTER.
IT HAS TURNED THE HUNDRED BLOCK OF CAPP STREET INTO.
W WENT AHEAD AND DECIDED ITSELF AT 15TH AND JULIAN IT HAS
TURNED THAT INTERSECTION INTO. WITH THAT RECORD WE OPPOSED
MISSION CABINS ONCE MISSION CABINS WERE CITED AT 1979
MISSION THE FENTANYL INFLUX HAPPENED AND GUNFIRE RANG OUT.
>> WE WERE CORRECT ON THAT. NONE OF THIS HAPPENED BEFORE
THESE FACILITIES WERE OPEN. SO WHEN WE ADD NEW FACILITIES
WE BRING THINGS TO NEIGHBORHOODS.
THE CITY'S SOLUTION TO THIS IS FOR MEDA AND MISSION HOUSING TO
DECIDE TO SITE PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FOR HOMELESS
PEOPLE. ADJACENT TO THE MARSHALL
ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, WE'RE TALKING ABOUT NONPROFIT
SALARIES. AT MEDA LOUIS GRANADOS MADE
$666,000 IN 2023. SAM MOSS MADE 300 TO $75,000 AT
MISSION HOUSING. MARTY'S A YIMBY.
THE ZOMBIES ATTACKED MARSHALL PARENTS.
THEY ATTACKED NONPROFITS AND THEY ATTACKED RESIDENTS AS
NIMBYS. EVEN AFTER WE FOUGHT FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AT 1979 MISSION BECAUSE WE DON'T WANT
ATTICS AND PSYCH CASES TO BE SITED NEXT TO A VULNERABLE
ELEMENTARY SCHOOL THAT HAS A HIGH PREPONDERANCE OF HOMELESS
KIDS, OF IMMIGRANT KIDS OF KIDS OF COLOR AND OF LOW INCOME
KIDS. >> WHAT'S NEXT?
AN ICE SUBSTATION IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD TO HELP OUT OUR
PARTNERS. WE'VE ASKED SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FOR HELP. SHE'S NOT CONTACTED US.
JACKIE FIELDER, WILL YOU COMMIT RIGHT HERE AND RIGHT NOW TO
FACILITATE MEDIATION BETWEEN MARSHALL PARENTS, RESIDENTS
AND NONPROFITS SO WE CAN MEET WITH MISSION HOUSING AND MEDA
TO FIND AN AMICABLE SOLUTION FOR THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR
HOMELESS FAMILIES THAT OUR NEIGHBORHOOD REALLY NEEDS.
>> WILL YOU DO THE CHAIR? SIR, IF YOU COULD ADDRESS THE
WHOLE BOARD THAT'S IN A MUCH NEXT SPEAKER PLACE.
>> YOU HAVE TWO MINUTES. >> MY NAME IS RICHARD PETERSON
. I WELCOME BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND PRESIDENT MANDELBAUM AND AND I HAVE TO ECHO A LOT OF
THE POLICIES AGAINST ROOMMATES THAT ARE GOING ON.
OF COURSE ME AS A LAWYER WHEN I WAS ACTUALLY PROACTIVE SAYING
LAW OVER $10,000 TO REMOVE A ROOMMATE THAT WAS ONLY AND WAS
A FRIEND THAT I WAS ONLY CHARGING $400 A MONTH TO LIVE
IN A NOWAY VALLEY BEDROOM APARTMENT WAS NOT APARTMENT
IN MY COTTAGE. >> SO I SYMPATHIZE.
BUT THE MOMENT THE THE MESSAGE FOR TODAY I THINK IS IS
COMPROMISE. WE GOT TO FIGURE OUT SOMETHING
TO COMPROMISE. THERE IS RESISTANCE GOING ON
UNDERSTANDABLE AND YOU HAVE TO HAVE STRONG RESISTANCE TO BE
ABLE TO MAKE A RATIONAL COMP REMISE AND THAT IS THE WORD
THAT I WOULD LIKE TO LEAVE YOU WITH TODAY.
IT'S NOT DEFINED AS IF YOU DEFI CERTAIN THINGS ARE GOING TO
CERTAIN VERY BAD THINGS ARE GOING TO HAPPEN.
>> I'M A I'M AN ATHEIST AND AND I'M CLASSIFIED WITH THE
COMMUNISTS THE SOCIALISTS AND THE TERRORISTS IN THE GROUP
OF FOUR AND SO I CAN SEE THAT IF YOU CAN'T REACH SOME KIND OF
COMPROMISE WHICH I UNDERSTAND OR I DO THINK THAT THE MAYOR IS
TRYING TO DO WE'RE GOING TO BE LOST ANYWAY.
I WANT TO I KEEP WEARING ONE PURPLE FOR A SHOUT OUT FOR THE
VALKYRIES AND SHOUT OUT TO MIMI HAAS LOVE YOU.
>> BYE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER AND GIVE MR. RAHMAN YOU
KNOW THERE'S NO THERE'S NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF APPROVAL
AND SUCH AS THAT WHEN IT STARTED JUST BEFORE YOU SPEAK,
SIR, ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO'D
LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
PLEASE STEP UP OTHERWISE THIS WILL BE OUR LAST SPEAKER OKAY.
>> WHEN IS THANK YOU ME NUMBER IS CAPRICCIO FLORIST DECIDED TO
STICK THE SINGLE A JAZZ IS PART OF ME BLAH BLAH STATUS HE ME
PETITION IS BARAK YEAH CAME THAT AUTUMN IS PLAYLAND ALLA
SIANA PLAYA DE LA OCEANA OCEAN BEACH PLAYLAND THANK YOU FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. >> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
. MADAM CLERK, COULD WE GO TO THE
FOR ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA, PLEASE CALL
ITEM SEVEN. ITEM SEVEN WAS INTRODUCED FOR
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
>> ITEM SEVEN IS A MOTION THAT THE BOARD CONVENE IN CLOSED
SESSION ON JULY 8TH 2025 FOR THE PURPOSE OF CONFERRING WITH
OR RECEIVING ADVICE FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY REGARDING THE
FOLLOWING EXISTING LITIGATION IN WHICH THE CITY IS THE
PETITIONER AND PACIFIC GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY IS AN
ADVERSE PARTY. >> SEE NO ONE ON THE ROSTER.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM SEVEN
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISE SIR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN MANDEL MEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> I HAVE NONE TO REPORT. MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? YES.
TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR
THE LATE MR. BYRON RET. >> COLLEAGUES, I THINK THAT
BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA, MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE
ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY THAN WE ARE
ADJOURNED. >> ANGELA